<?xml version="1.0"?>
<int-org-entry id="AFESD.IO" id-root="afesd.io" iso="afesd.io" original-filename="wb02030.txt" print-style="PGWIDTH" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-ENTRYREF" usage="edio mena"  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:pubid:EuropaWorld.com:doctypes:dita:europaworld.xsd">
     <int-org-entry-head>
          <int-org-name-group type="MAIN">
               <org-entry-name>Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development</org-entry-name>
               <abbr>AFESD</abbr>
          </int-org-name-group>
     </int-org-entry-head>
     <alt-heading type="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE" usage="edio">MAJOR NON-UN ORGANIZATIONS</alt-heading>
     <alt-heading type="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE" usage="mena">REGIONAL ORGANIZATIONS</alt-heading>
     <alt-heading type="COUNTRY-SHORT-TITLECASE">AFESD</alt-heading>
     <int-org-block>
          <address-block>
               <address type="POSTAL">
                    <verbatim-address>POB 21923, Safat, 13080 Kuwait</verbatim-address>
               </address>
               <telephone alsofax="N">24959000</telephone>
               <fax>24959390</fax>
               <email>hq@arabfund.org</email>
               <internet>www.arabfund.org</internet>
          </address-block>
          <p id="AFESD.IO.48">Established in 1968 by the Economic Council of the Arab League, the Fund began its operations in 1974. It participates in the financing of public and private economic and social development projects in the Arab states, and provides grants and expertise to member states.</p>
          <int-org-section id="AFESD.IO.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Members</heading>
               <p>All member countries of the League of Arab States.</p>
          </int-org-section>
     </int-org-block>
     <int-org-section id="AFESD.IO.2" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Organization</heading>
          <heading-note>September 2023</heading-note>
          <int-org-section id="AFESD.IO.3" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Board of Governors</heading>
               <p id="AFESD.IO.50">The Board of Governors consists of a Governor and an Alternate Governor appointed by each member of the Fund. The Board of Governors is considered as the General Assembly of the Fund, and has all powers.</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="AFESD.IO.4" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Board of Directors</heading>
               <p id="AFESD.IO.51">The Board of Directors is composed of eight Directors elected by the Board of Governors for a renewable term of two years. The Board is charged with all the activities of the Fund and exercises the powers delegated to it by the Board of Governors.</p>
               <dir-list>
                    <dir-entry id="AFESD.IO.53" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                         <dir-entry-name>Director-General and Chairman of the Board of Directors</dir-entry-name>
                         <person-group>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <forename>Bader M.</forename>
                                        <surname>al-Asaad</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>Kuwait</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </person-group>
                    </dir-entry>
               </dir-list>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="AFESD.IO.5" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Financial Structure</heading>
               <p id="AFESD.IO.54">In April 2013 the Board of Governors agreed to increase the Fund’s subscribed capital to 3,000 Kuwaiti dinars (KD) from KD&#160;2,000m. (effected through a transfer of KD&#160;500m. from the Fund’s additional capital reserves to paid-up capital, and through an increase in member states’ subscriptions that was paid in instalments over the ensuing five years); the Fund’s authorized capital, meanwhile, was increased to KD&#160;4,000m. By 31 March 2023 the Fund’s paid-up capital stood at KD&#160;2,903m. At that time shareholders’ equity amounted to KD&#160;3,980m. </p>
          </int-org-section>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="AFESD.IO.7" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Activities</heading>
          <p>The Fund aims to contribute to the financing of economic and social development projects in the Arab states and countries by means of loans granted on concessionary terms to governments and public enterprises and corporations; private sector projects may also be supported through the provision of loans and guarantees, as well as other financial, technical and advisory services. In November 2016 the Board of Directors agreed to reduce the rate of interest on the repayment of loans (over a term of 30 years, increased from 22) from 2.5% to 2% for low-income member states, and from 3% to 2.5% for other beneficiary states. Projects that strengthen the interdependence of Arab countries and enhance social development are prioritized.</p>
          <p>In February 2021 the Board of Directors approved a medium-term strategy, covering the period 2021-24, with the following priorities: supporting the development of regional infrastructure, including energy generation, with a particular emphasis on advancing renewable energy sources; expansion of the production sector; provision of technical and institutional assistance to human development initiatives focused on generating employment; preservation of the environment and reduction of carbon emissions; strengthening small and medium-sized enterprises; and supporting joint Arab projects.</p>
          <p>During 2022 the Fund approved three loans, totalling KD&#8201;52.0m., comprising a KD&#8201;10.0m. loan to support the supply of drinking water in Kiffa, Mauritania; a KD&#8201;25,0m. loan for a similar drinking water supply initiative in Nouakchott; and also KD&#8201;17.0m. loan for an integrated agricultural development project in southern Kasserine Governate, Tunisia. At the end of 2022 total lending since 1974 amounted to KD&#160;11,191.0m. for 709 loans. By the end of 2022 AFESD lending had financed 601 projects in 18 Arab countries (covering around 27.4% of the total cost of those initiatives); during that period some 30.6% of the total value of the loans was allocated to energy and electricity initiatives, 24.8% to transport, 13.6% to water and sewerage, and 13.5% to agriculture and rural development.</p>
          <p>In 2022 the Fund extended 11 national grants, amounting to KD&#8201;1.1m. Some 94.3% of the finance channelled through national grants in that year supported institutional support and training, 4.7% was for general studies and research, and 1.0% for seminars and conferences. The Fund also approved four inter-Arab grants, at a cost of KD&#8201;400,000; in this respect, 46.8% was allocated to institutional support and training, 31.9% for general studies and research, and 21.3% for seminars and conferences. The cumulative total number of grants provided by the end of 2022 was 1,284, with a value of KD&#8201;254.9m.</p>
          <p>The Fund allocated KD&#8201;11.4m. in 2022 (equivalent to 10% of its 2021 net profits) to its Urgent Program to Support the Palestinian People. Cumulative contributions by the end of 2022 since the Program’s establishment in 2001 amounted to KD&#8201;189.9m. By the end of 2022 the Fund’s Programme to Support the Resistance of Jerusalem had received two instalments, in 2010 and 2016, that totalled KD&#8201;29.6m.</p>
          <p>The Fund administers a Special Account, inaugurated in October 2010, which finances and offers technical and advisory assistance to small and medium-sized private sector commercial and developmental projects. By the end of 2022 49 loans totalling US&#8201;$1,591m. had been approved through the Special Account.</p>
          <p id="AFESD.IO.108">
      The Fund acts as the secretariat of the Co-ordination Group of Arab National and Regional Development Financing Institutions. These organizations work together to produce a 
      <i>Joint Arab Economic Report,</i>
       which considers economic and social developments in the Arab states. The Fund co-operates with other organizations in preparing regional studies and conferences, for example in the areas of human resource development, demographic research and private sector financing of infrastructure projects.
    </p>
          <p>AFESD and the World Bank were jointly to support the preparation process to establish an Arab common market for electricity, in accordance with a Memorandum of Understanding approved in September 2016 by Arab League ministers responsible for foreign affairs. In November 2019 AFESD, the Arab League and the World Bank organized the First Pan-Arab Energy Trade Conference, in Cairo, Egypt.</p>
          <p usage="edio">
      In September 2011 the Fund endorsed the so-called Deauville Partnership, which had been established by the then Group of Eight industrialized countries in May in order to assist countries in the Middle East and North Africa undergoing social and economic transformations. The Fund joined some nine other international financial institutions active in the region to establish a Co-ordination Platform to facilitate and promote collaboration among the institutions extending assistance under the Partnership. In 2013 the Board of Directors approved the Fund’s participation in the capital of a fund established by the 
      <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-UN.1966">International Finance Corporation</xr>
       to invest in private sector facilities and companies in the Middle East and North Africa.
    </p>
          <p>The Fund manages an Arab Fund Fellowships Program, which since its inception in 1997 has awarded scholarship grants (178 by 2022, of which 163 were implemented) to enable Arab citizens with doctorates to conduct advanced research and to lecture at top universities worldwide. A new Abdlatif Y. Al-Hamad Development Award in the Arab World was introduced in 2022.</p>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="AFESD.IO.37" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Publications</heading>
          <publ-list>
               <publ-entry>
                    <publ-name>Annual Report</publ-name>
               </publ-entry>
               <publ-entry>
                    <publ-name>Joint Arab Economic Report</publ-name>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">annually</content-note>
               </publ-entry>
          </publ-list>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="IO-AFESD.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF" usage="mena">
          <heading>Statistics</heading>
          <table-block id="AFESD.IO.112" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="TABLE-BLOCKREF" type="OTHER" usage="mena">
               <table-heading>Loans by Sector</table-heading>
               <table pgwide="NO" style="WITH-RULES">
                    <tgroup cols="5">
                         <colspec colname="1" colwidth="8.0cm" />
                         <colspec colname="2" colwidth="4.0cm" />
                         <colspec colname="3" colwidth="3.5cm" />
                         <colspec colname="5" colwidth="1.0cm" />
                         <colspec colname="6" colwidth="3.5cm" />
                         <thead>
                              <row>
                                   <entry align="left" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="center" nameend="3" namest="2" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">2022</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" nameend="6" namest="5" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">1974-2022</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry align="left" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Sector</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Amount (KD million)</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">%</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">%</entry>
                              </row>
                         </thead>
                         <tbody>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">Infrastructure sectors</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">35.0</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">67.3</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">70.2</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">&#8195;Transport</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">24.8</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">&#8195;Telecommunications</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">1.3</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">&#8195;Energy and electricity</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">30.6</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">&#8195;Water and sewerage</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">35.0</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">67.3</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">13.6</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">Productive sectors</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">17.0</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">32.7</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">18.1</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">&#8195;Industry and mining</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">4.6</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry align="left" style="DOT-LEADER">&#8195;Agriculture and rural &#8195;development</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">17.0</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">32.7</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">13.5</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER">Social services</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">8.9</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry align="left" style="DOT-LEADER">Other</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">—</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">2.7</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry align="left" style="DOT-LEADER">
                                        <b>Total</b>
                                   </entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">10.4</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">100.0</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">100.0</entry>
                              </row>
                         </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
               </table>
               <sources>
                    <source-head>Source</source-head>
                    <source-info>
          AFESD, 
          <i>Annual Report 2022</i>
                    </source-info>
               </sources>
          </table-block>
          <table-block id="AFESD.IO.113" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="TABLE-BLOCKREF" type="OTHER">
               <table-heading>Loans Approved, 2022</table-heading>
               <table pgwide="NO" style="WITH-RULES">
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                         <colspec colname="1" colwidth="5.0cm" />
                         <colspec colname="COLSPEC0" colwidth="11.00cm" />
                         <colspec colname="6" colwidth="4cm" />
                         <thead>
                              <row>
                                   <entry align="left" style="NO-DOT-LEADER" />
                                   <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Purpose</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Amount (KD million)</entry>
                              </row>
                         </thead>
                         <tbody>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER" valign="top">Mauritania</entry>
                                   <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Supply of drinking water in Kiffa</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">10.0</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER" valign="top" />
                                   <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Supply of drinking water in Nouakchott</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">25.0</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                   <entry style="DOT-LEADER" valign="top">Tunisia</entry>
                                   <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Integrated agricultural development project in southern Kasserine Governate</entry>
                                   <entry align="right" style="NO-DOT-LEADER">17.0</entry>
                              </row>
                         </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
               </table>
               <sources>
                    <source-head>Source</source-head>
                    <source-info>
          AFESD, 
          <i>Annual Report 2022</i>
                    </source-info>
               </sources>
          </table-block>
     </int-org-section>
</int-org-entry>