<?xml version="1.0"?>
<int-org-entry id="AU.IO" id-root="au.io" iso="au.io" original-filename="wb02062.txt" print-style="PGWIDTH" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-ENTRYREF" usage="ewyb edio mena ass"  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:pubid:EuropaWorld.com:doctypes:dita:europaworld.xsd">
     <int-org-entry-head>
          <int-org-name-group type="MAIN">
               <org-entry-name>African Union</org-entry-name>
               <abbr>AU</abbr>
          </int-org-name-group>
     </int-org-entry-head>
     <alt-heading type="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE" usage="ewyb">INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS</alt-heading>
     <alt-heading type="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE" usage="edio">MAJOR NON-UN ORGANIZATIONS</alt-heading>
     <alt-heading type="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE" usage="ass mena">REGIONAL ORGANIZATIONS</alt-heading>
     <alt-heading type="COUNTRY-SHORT-TITLECASE">African Union</alt-heading>
     <int-org-block>
          <address-block>
               <address type="POSTAL">
                    <verbatim-address>Roosevelt St, W21K19, POB 3243, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</verbatim-address>
               </address>
               <telephone alsofax="N">(11) 5517700</telephone>
               <fax>(11) 5517844</fax>
               <email>dic@africa-union.org</email>
               <internet>au.int</internet>
          </address-block>
          <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.3">The Constitutive Act of the African Union entered into force in May 2001. In July 2002 the AU became fully operational, replacing the Organization of African Unity (OAU), which had been founded in 1963. The AU aims to support unity, soli­darity and peace among African states; to defend African common positions on issues of shared interest; to promote sustainable development and political and socioeconomic integration; and to encourage human rights, democratic principles and good governance in all member states.</p>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.102" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Members</heading>
               <table-block-simple id="WB02062.IO.TXT.103" type="OTHER" usage="edio ass">
                    <table pgwide="NO" style="WITHOUT-RULES">
                         <tgroup cols="3">
                              <colspec colwidth="6.7cm" />
                              <colspec colwidth="6.7cm" />
                              <colspec colwidth="6.6cm" />
                              <tbody>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Algeria</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Eswatini</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Namibia</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Angola</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Ethiopia</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">
                  Niger
                  <endnoteref idref="AU.IO.MALI.1" ref-symbol="*" />
                                        </entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Benin</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">
                  Gabon
                  <endnoteref idref="AU.IO.MALI.1" ref-symbol="*" />
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Nigeria</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Botswana</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">The Gambia</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Rwanda</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">
                  Burkina Faso
                  <endnoteref idref="AU.IO.MALI.1" ref-symbol="*" />
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Ghana</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">São Tomé and Príncipe</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Burundi</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">
                  Guinea
                  <endnoteref idref="AU.IO.MALI.1" ref-symbol="*" />
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Senegal</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Cabo Verde</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Guinea-Bissau</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Seychelles</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Cameroon</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Kenya</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Sierra Leone</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Central African Republic</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Lesotho</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Somalia</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Chad</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Liberia</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">South Africa</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Comoros</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Libya</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">South Sudan</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Congo, Democratic Republic</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Madagascar</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">
                  Sudan
                  <endnoteref idref="AU.IO.MALI.1" ref-symbol="*" />
                                        </entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Congo, Republic</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Malawi</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Tanzania</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Côte d'Ivoire</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">
                  Mali
                  <endnoteref idref="AU.IO.MALI.1" ref-symbol="*" />
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Togo</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Dijbouti</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Mauritania</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Tunisia</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Egypt</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Mauritius</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Uganda</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Equatorial Guinea</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">
                  Morocco
                  <endnoteref idref="WB02062.IO.TXT.69" ref-symbol="†" />
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Zambia</entry>
                                   </row>
                                   <row>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Eritrea</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Mozambique</entry>
                                        <entry style="NO-DOT-LEADER">Zimbabwe</entry>
                                   </row>
                              </tbody>
                         </tgroup>
                    </table>
                    <endnote id="AU.IO.MALI.1" ref-symbol="*">On 1 June 2021, following the overthrow in late May by the Malian military of the leadership of Mali’s transitional administration, the Peace and Security Council suspended that country’s participation in the activities of the AU. Guinea was suspended on 10 September, following the overthrow of President Alpha Condé. On 26 October Sudan was suspended, in response to the removal by that country’s military of the civilian transitional government. In January 2022 Burkina Faso was also suspended pending the restoration of constitutional order following a military coup. Niger was suspended on 22 August 2023, following the overthrow of President Mohamed Bazoum in the previous month. On 31 August Gabon was suspended, the military having usurped power on the previous day from President Ali Bongo Ondimba</endnote>
                    <endnote id="WB02062.IO.TXT.69" ref-symbol="†">The Sahrawi Arab Democratic Republic (SADR-Western Sahara) was admitted to the OAU in February 1982, following recognition by more than one-half of the member states, but its membership was disputed by Morocco and other countries which claimed that a two-thirds' majority was needed to admit a state whose existence was in question. Morocco withdrew from the OAU with effect from November 1985. In July 2016 a Moroccan special envoy met AU leaders to discuss the possibility of Morocco’s accession to the AU; it was readmitted at the 28th session of the Assembly in January 2017. The SADR ratified the Constitutive Act in December 2000 and is a full member of the AU</endnote>
               </table-block-simple>
               <p usage="ewyb mena">All countries in Africa are members of the AU. The membership is divided into five regions: Central Africa (nine countries); Eastern Africa (14); Northern Africa (seven: including the Sahrawi Arab Democratic Republic—SADR); Southern Africa (10); and Western Africa (15) (totalling 55). The SADR was admitted to the OAU in February 1982, following recognition by more than one-half of the member states, but its membership was disputed by Morocco and other countries which claimed that a two-thirds' majority was needed to admit a state whose existence was in question. Morocco withdrew from the OAU (from November 1985) in protest. In July 2016 a Moroccan special envoy met AU leaders to discuss the possibility of Morocco’s accession to the AU; it was readmitted at the 28th session of the Assembly in January 2017. The SADR ratified the Constitutive Act in December 2000 and is a full member of the AU.</p>
               <p usage="ewyb mena">By early 2024 the following countries were suspended from participation in activities of the organization: Burkina Faso, Gabon, Mali, Niger, Sudan.</p>
          </int-org-section>
     </int-org-block>
     <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.104" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Organization</heading>
          <heading-note>April 2024</heading-note>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.105" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Assembly</heading>
               <p>The Assembly, comprising heads of state and of government, is the supreme organ of the Union and meets usually twice a year to determine and monitor the organization's priorities and common policies and to adopt its annual work programme. Resolutions are passed by a two-thirds' majority, procedural matters by a simple majority. Extraordinary sessions may be convened at the request of a member state and on approval by a two-thirds' majority. The Assembly ensures compliance by member states with decisions of the Union, appoints judges of the African Court of Human and Peoples’ Rights, and hears and settles disputes between member states. It may also appoint individual African heads of state and government to lead the implementation of specific high priority AU initiatives. The 36th ordinary session of the Assembly took place in February 2024, in Addis Ababa, with a particular focus on the AU’s theme for that year: `Educate and Skill Africa for the 21st Century’. The Chairperson of the Assembly is assisted by a four-member Bureau.</p>
               <dir-list>
                    <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                         <dir-entry-name>Chairperson (2024/25)</dir-entry-name>
                         <person-group>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <forename>Mohamed Ould Cheikh</forename>
                                        <surname>al-Ghazouani</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>President of Mauritania</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </person-group>
                    </dir-entry>
               </dir-list>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.106" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Executive Council</heading>
               <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.73">The Council consists of ministers responsible for foreign affairs and others and meets at least twice a year, with provision for extraordinary sessions. It prepares meetings of, and is responsible to, the Assembly; determines the issues to be submitted to the Assembly for decision; co-ordinates and harmonizes the policies, activities and initiatives of the Union in areas of common interest to member states; and monitors the implementation of policies and decisions of the Assembly.</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.107" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Permanent Representatives Committee</heading>
               <p>The Committee, which comprises ambassadors accredited to the AU, meets at least once a month. It is responsible to the Executive Council, which it advises, and whose meetings, including matters for the agenda and draft decisions, it prepares.</p>
               <p usage="edio ass">In July 2021 the Chairperson of the AU Commission accepted the credentials of Israel’s Ambassador to Ethiopia: the AU’s membership was divided in response. In February 2024, during the 37th AU Assembly, the Chairperson of the Commission designated Israel’s ongoing offensive against Gaza as a `flagrant violation’ of international humanitarian law.</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.108" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Commission</heading>
               <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.75">The Commission is the permanent secretariat of the AU, reporting to the Executive Council. It comprises a Chairperson (elected for a four-year term of office by the Assembly), Deputy Chairperson and six further Commissioners, responsible for: Political Affairs, Peace and Security; Infrastructure and Energy; Health, Humanitarian Affairs and Social Development; Education, Science, Technology and Innovation; Agriculture, Rural Development, Blue Economy and Sustainable Environment; and Economic Development, Trade, Industry and Mining. They are elected on the basis of equal geographical distribution. Members of the Commission serve a term of four years and may stand for re-election for one further term of office. A Panel of Eminent Africans was established to oversee the equitable selection of Commission candidates.</p>
               <p usage="edio ass">The Commission deals with administrative issues, implements the decisions of the Union, and acts as the custodian of the Constitutive Act and Protocols, and other agreements, and areas where a common position has been established by member states. It has responsibility for the co-ordination of AU activities and meetings.</p>
               <dir-list>
                    <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                         <dir-entry-name>Chairperson (2021-24)</dir-entry-name>
                         <person-group>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <forename>Moussa</forename>
                                        <surname>Faki Mahamat</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>Chad</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </person-group>
                    </dir-entry>
                    <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF" usage="ass">
                         <dir-entry-name>Director-General</dir-entry-name>
                         <person-group>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <forename>Fathallah</forename>
                                        <surname>Sijilmassi</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>Morocco</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </person-group>
                    </dir-entry>
               </dir-list>
               <int-org-section id="AU.IO.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF" usage="ass mena">
                    <heading>Commissioners</heading>
                    <dir-list>
                         <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                              <dir-entry-name>Economic Development, Trade, Industry and Mining</dir-entry-name>
                              <person-group>
                                   <person>
                                        <person-name>
                                             <forename>Albert</forename>
                                             <surname>Muchanga</surname>
                                        </person-name>
                                        <person-note>Zambia</person-note>
                                   </person>
                              </person-group>
                         </dir-entry>
                         <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                              <dir-entry-name>Infrastructure and Energy</dir-entry-name>
                              <person-group>
                                   <person>
                                        <person-name>
                                             <title>Dr</title>
                                             <forename>Amani</forename>
                                             <surname>Abou-Zeid</surname>
                                        </person-name>
                                        <person-note>Egypt</person-note>
                                   </person>
                              </person-group>
                         </dir-entry>
                         <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                              <dir-entry-name>Political Affairs, Peace and Security</dir-entry-name>
                              <person-group>
                                   <person>
                                        <person-name>
                                             <forename>Bankole</forename>
                                             <surname>Adeoye</surname>
                                        </person-name>
                                        <person-note>Nigeria</person-note>
                                   </person>
                              </person-group>
                         </dir-entry>
                         <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                              <dir-entry-name>Agriculture, Rural Development, Blue Economy and Sustainable Environment</dir-entry-name>
                              <person-group>
                                   <person>
                                        <person-name>
                                             <forename>Josefa Leonel Correa</forename>
                                             <surname>Sacko</surname>
                                        </person-name>
                                        <person-note>Angola</person-note>
                                   </person>
                              </person-group>
                         </dir-entry>
                         <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                              <dir-entry-name>Health, Humanitarian Affairs and Social Development</dir-entry-name>
                              <person-group>
                                   <person>
                                        <person-name>
                                             <forename>Cessouma</forename>
                                             <surname>Minata Samate</surname>
                                        </person-name>
                                        <person-note>Burkina Faso</person-note>
                                   </person>
                              </person-group>
                         </dir-entry>
                         <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                              <dir-entry-name>Education, Science, Technology and Innovation</dir-entry-name>
                              <person-group>
                                   <person>
                                        <person-name>
                                             <title>Prof.</title>
                                             <forename>Mohamed</forename>
                                             <surname>Belhocine</surname>
                                        </person-name>
                                        <person-note>Algeria</person-note>
                                   </person>
                              </person-group>
                         </dir-entry>
                    </dir-list>
               </int-org-section>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.109" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Specialized Technical Committees</heading>
               <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.77">
        There are specialized committees—comprising member states’ ministers and senior officials—for agriculture, rural development, water and environment; communication and information communications technology; defence, safety and security; education, science and technology; finance, monetary affairs, economic planning and integration; gender and women’s empowerment; health, population and drug control; justice and legal affairs; migration, refugees and internally displaced persons; public service, local government, urban development and decentralization; social development, labour and employment; trade, industry and minerals; transport, transcontinental and inter-regional infrastructure, energy and tourism; and youth, culture and sports. The Nairobi, Kenya-based African Institute for Remittances—supported by the European Commission, the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="ADB.IO">African Development Bank (AfDB)</xr>
        , the World Bank, and the International Organization for Migration—is a Specialized Technical Office of the AU Commission.
      </p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.109.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Pan-African Parliament</heading>
               <p>The Pan-African Parliament, established in 2004 and located in Midrand, South Africa, comprises five deputies (including at least one woman) from each AU member state, presided over by an elected President. The President and four Vice-Presidents must equitably represent the five African regions. The Parliament convenes at least twice a year; an extraordinary session may be called by a two-thirds’ majority of the members. The Parliament has only advisory and consultative powers; its eventual evolution into an institution with full legislative authority is envisaged. In June 2023 the Parliament organized a workshop focused on enhancing access to African legal information.</p>
               <dir-list>
                    <dir-entry sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="DIR-ENTRYREF">
                         <dir-entry-name>President</dir-entry-name>
                         <person-group>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <title>Hon. Chief</title>
                                        <forename>Fortune Zephania</forename>
                                        <surname>Charumbira</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>Zimbabwe</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </person-group>
                         <!--Charumbira re-elected iii.24-->
                    </dir-entry>
               </dir-list>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="IO-AFUNION.0023" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Judicial and Human Rights Institutions</heading>
               <org-list>
                    <org-entry id="IO-AFUNION.0023.1" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                         <org-entry-head>
                              <org-entry-name>African Commission on Human and Peoples’ Rights (ACHPR)</org-entry-name>
                         </org-entry-head>
                         <address-block>
                              <address type="POSTAL">
                                   <verbatim-address>POB 673, Banjul, The Gambia </verbatim-address>
                              </address>
                              <telephone alsofax="N">441-05-05</telephone>
                              <fax>441-05-04</fax>
                              <email>au-banjul@african-union.org</email>
                              <internet>achpr.au.int</internet>
                         </address-block>
                         <found-date>1987, in accordance with and a year after the entry into force of the African Charter on Human and Peoples’ Rights</found-date>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">tasked with promoting and protecting human rights and basic freedoms, and with interpreting the provisions of the Charter</content-note>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">it comprises 11 Commissioners who are appointed by the AU Assembly for six-year terms in office and meet at least twice a year; a secretariat provides administrative, technical and logistical support. Recommendations of the Commission are not legally-binding; it may use its `good offices’ to support states to abide by the recommendations. Other subsidiary mechanisms to support the Commission’s activities include special rapporteurs, working groups and advisory committees, all of which are required to report regularly on their findings. In 2016 the ACHPR issued a set of Principles and Guidelines on Human Rights while Countering Terrorism in Africa</content-note>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">79th ordinary session: May-June 2024</content-note>
                         <role-group>
                              <role>Exec. Sec.</role>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <forename>Abiola</forename>
                                        <surname>Idowu-Ojo</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>acting</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </role-group>
                    </org-entry>
                    <org-entry id="IO-AFUNION.0023.2" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                         <org-entry-head>
                              <org-entry-name>African Court of Human and Peoples’ Rights</org-entry-name>
                         </org-entry-head>
                         <address-block>
                              <address type="POSTAL">
                                   <verbatim-address>POB 6274, Arusha, Tanzania</verbatim-address>
                              </address>
                              <telephone alsofax="N">(27) 2970430</telephone>
                              <email>registrar@african-court.org</email>
                              <internet>www.african-court.org</internet>
                         </address-block>
                         <found-date>Jan. 2004, upon the entry into force of the Protocol to the African Charter on Human and Peoples’ Rights (adopted in June 1998)</found-date>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">consists of 11 judges, elected by the AU Assembly. Its role is to support the ACHPR and rule on the interpretation and application of the Charter. A Protocol to establish an African Court of Justice was adopted in July 2003 (it entered into effect in Feb. 2009 after receiving the required number of ratifications but has never been operational). In July 2008 the AU summit determined to merge the courts and adopted a Protocol on the Statute of the African Court of Justice and Human Rights; by Jan. 2024 the Protocol had been signed by 33 states and ratified by eight (requiring 15 ratifications to enter into force)</content-note>
                    </org-entry>
               </org-list>
               <p>In February 2020 the AU Assembly adopted the following new entities: the Sudan-based Continental Operational Centre for Combating Irregular Migration; the Mali-based African Centre for Study and Research on Migration; the African Migration Observatory (based in Morocco); the Algeria-based AU Mechanism for Police Co-operation (AFRIPOL); the AU Centre for Post-Conflict Reconstruction and Development (Egypt); and the African Observatory of Science, Technology and Innovation (Equatorial Guinea).</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="IO-AFUNION.78" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Peace and Security Council</heading>
               <p id="IO-AFUNION.78.1">The Protocol to the Constitutive Act of the African Union Relating to the Peace and Security Council of the African Union entered into force on 26 December 2003; the 15-member elected Council was formally inaugurated in May 2004 (Northern Africa is represented on the Council by two seats; Central Africa, Eastern Africa, and Southern Africa each by three seats; and Western Africa by four seats). It acts as a decision making body for the prevention, management and resolution of conflicts.</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="IO-AFUNION.79" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Economic, Social and Cultural Council</heading>
               <p id="IO-AFUNION.79.1">The Economic, Social and Cultural Council, inaugur­ated in March 2005, comprises representatives of civic, professional and cultural bodies at national, regional and diaspora level. Its main statutory organs are an elected General Assembly; a Standing Committee; a Credentials Committee; and Sectoral Cluster Communities, tasked with formulating opinions and advising on AU decision making.</p>
               <!--~ second election to the Assembly-->
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.117" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Development Agency</heading>
               <org-list>
                    <org-entry id="WB02062.IO.TXT.100" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                         <org-entry-head>
                              <org-entry-name>African Union Development Agency</org-entry-name>
                              <abbr>AUDA-NEPAD</abbr>
                         </org-entry-head>
                         <address-block>
                              <address type="POSTAL">
                                   <verbatim-address>230 15th Rd, Randjespark, Midrand 1685, South Africa</verbatim-address>
                              </address>
                              <telephone alsofax="N">(11) 2563600</telephone>
                              <email>info@nepad.org</email>
                              <internet>www.nepad.org</internet>
                         </address-block>
                         <found-date>2018</found-date>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">
            a successor to the New Partnership for Africa's Development (NEPAD) Planning and Co-ordination Agency, the technical body established in 2010 to implement NEPAD projects—NEPAD having been launched in 2001 as a long-term strategy to promote socioeconomic devt in Africa. A voluntary African Peer Review Mechanism (APRM), established under NEPAD auspices in accordance with a Declaration on Democracy, Political, Economic and Corporate Governance adopted by AU heads of state and government in June 2002, assesses states’ conduct in the areas of democracy and political governance; economic governance and management; corporate governance; and socioeconomic governance; in July 2023 the APRM issued the 
            <publ-name>Africa Governance Report 2023</publ-name>
            , the 3rd in a series—with a focus on unconstitutional changes of government
          </content-note>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">
            NEPAD’s Programme for Infrastructure Development in Africa (PIDA), of which the 
            <xr pageref="N" ref="ADB.IO">AfDB</xr>
             is the executing agency, was initiated in 2010 with the aim of developing the continental energy, information and communications technology, transport and transboundary water resources infrastructures; a second PIDA Priority Action Plan (PIDA PAP 2) was being implemented over the period 2011-30, with NEPAD-AUDA as lead co-ordinating agency; in Feb. 2021 AU leaders approved 69 PIDA PAP 2 projects
          </content-note>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">a Continental Africa Water Investment Programme was initiated at that time</content-note>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">maintains centres of excellence on Climate Resilience; Rural Resources and Food Systems; Human Capital and Institutions Development; and Supply Chains and Logistics; and a Science and Technology and Innovation Hub</content-note>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">A Heads of State and Government Orientation Cttee provides leadership to the NEPAD process, determines policies, priorities and programmes of action and, through its Chair., reports directly to the AU Assembly</content-note>
                         <content-note style="NORMAL">the UN allocated US&#8201;$9.6m. in support of the agency under its 2024 budget</content-note>
                         <role-group>
                              <role>CEO</role>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <forename>Nardos</forename>
                                        <surname>Bekele-Thomas</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>Ethiopia</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </role-group>
                    </org-entry>
               </org-list>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="AU.IO.100" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>African Continental Free Trade Area Secretariat</heading>
               <org-list>
                    <org-entry media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                         <org-entry-head>
                              <org-entry-name>AfCFTA Secretariat</org-entry-name>
                         </org-entry-head>
                         <address-block>
                              <address type="POSTAL">
                                   <verbatim-address>Africa Trade House, Ambassadorial Enclave, Liberia Rd, Ridge, Accra, Ghana</verbatim-address>
                              </address>
                              <email>info@au-afcfta.org</email>
                              <internet>au-afcfta.org</internet>
                         </address-block>
                         <found-date>2019 to facilitate the implementation of the AfCFTA (q.v.)</found-date>
                         <role-group>
                              <role>Sec.-Gen.</role>
                              <person>
                                   <person-name>
                                        <forename>Wamkele Keabetswe</forename>
                                        <surname>Mene</surname>
                                   </person-name>
                                   <person-note>South Africa</person-note>
                              </person>
                         </role-group>
                    </org-entry>
               </org-list>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="IO-AFUNION.TXT.78.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF" usage="edio">
               <heading>Proposed Financial Institutions</heading>
               <p id="IO-AFUNION.TXT.78" usage="edio ass">The Constitutive Act envisaged the establishment of three financial institutions to the financing of programmes and projects and support regional integration: an African Central Bank; a Pan-African Stock Exchange; an African Monetary Fund (AMF); and an African Investment Bank (AIB). A protocol and statute for the establishment of the AIB was approved by the AU Assembly in 2009. In June 2014 a protocol and statute for the AMF, which was to be located in Yaoundé, Cameroon, were adopted by the 23rd AU summit meeting.</p>
          </int-org-section>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.111" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Activities</heading>
          <p>In May 1963 30 African heads of state adopted the Charter of the Organization of African Unity (OAU). An Abuja Treaty Establishing the African Economic Community (AEC) was signed in June 1991, and entered into force in May 1994. </p>
          <p usage="edio ass mena">An extraordinary summit meeting, convened in September 1999, in Sirte, Libya, at the request of the then Libyan leader Col Muammar al-Qaddafi, determined to establish an African Union, based on the principles and objectives of the OAU and the AEC, but strengthening African co-operation, development and integration. Heads of state declared their commitment to accelerating the establishment of regional institutions as well as the implementation of economic and monetary union, as provided for by the Abuja Treaty.</p>
          <p>In July 2000 at a summit meeting of the OAU held in Lomé, Togo, 27 heads of state and of government signed the draft Constitutive Act of the African Union, which was to enter into force after ratification by two-thirds of member states' legislatures; this was achieved in May 2001. The Union was inaugurated, replacing the OAU, on 9 July 2002, at a summit meeting held in Durban, South Africa. During the transitional year a review of all OAU treaties was undertaken and those deemed relevant were retained by the AU. The AU operates on the basis of both the Constitutive Act and the Abuja Treaty.</p>
          <p usage="edio">The 27th ordinary session of the AU Assembly, convened in July 2016, determined to impose, with effect from 2017, a 0.2% levy on certain goods imported into the continent to fund the organization’s operational projects, programmes and peace and security operations budget.</p>
          <p usage="edio">In May 2012, with a view to increasing the involvement in the African development agenda of people of African origin living beyond the continent, the AU hosted the first Global African Diaspora Summit, in Midrand, South Africa. The Summit was proceeded by the first gathering of parliamentarians of African descent; this was, in 2014, consolidated into a new Global Parliamentarian Diaspora Network.</p>
          <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In February 2021 the 34th AU Assembly declared the Decade of African Roots and Diasporas, covering 2021-31, with the aim of furthering diaspora engagement in the continental development agenda.</p>
          <int-org-section id="IO-AU.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Agenda 2063</heading>
               <p>
        The May 2013 session of the Assembly issued a 50th Anniversary Solemn Declaration, which outlined a vision and series of ideals for the economic and social transformation of the continent over the coming 50 years. These were to be translated into concrete actions and objectives by a joint programme with the AfDB and the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-UN.1052">UN Economic Commission for Africa</xr>
         (ECA) known as Agenda 2063, within the context of which 20 African Development Goals were to be developed. Endorsed by AU heads of state and of government in January 2015, the finalized Agenda 2063 was underpinned by the following so-called African Aspirations: a prosperous Africa, based on inclusive growth and sustainable development; an integrated, politically united continent, based on the ideals of Pan-Africanism and a vision of Africa’s Renaissance; an Africa of good governance, democracy, respect for human rights, justice and the rule of law; a peaceful and secure Africa; a strong continental cultural identity, based on common heritage, values and ethics; people-driven continental development (with a particular focus on women and youth); and Africa as a strong, united, influential global player and partner. In June 2015 the AU summit adopted `The First Ten-Year Implementation Plan of Agenda 2063 and its Financing Mechanism’. The following were designated as Agenda 2063 flagship initiatives: (i) connecting all African capital cities and commercial centres through an African Integrated High Speed Train Network; (ii) formulating an African Commodities Strategy, aimed at transforming the continent from a supplier of raw materials to an active user—for the economic benefit of Africans—of its own resources; (iii) developing the AfCFTA; (iv) promoting free movement of people and an African passport; (v) silencing guns: ending all conflicts, genocides and gender-based violence, and introducing an African Human Security Index; (vi) implementing the proposed 43,200 KW Grand Inga Dam hydropower project on the River Congo, Democratic Republic of the Congo—DRC , which, it was envisaged, would support regional power pools; (vii) establishing a Single African Air Transport Market; (viii) promoting an annual African Economic Forum; (ix) establishing the proposed African continental financial institutions; (x) putting in place a Pan-African E-Network, including a strong intra-African broadband terrestrial infrastructure; (xi) implementing an Africa Outer Space Strategy, to promote climate forecasting, disaster management, remote sensing, defence and security, and agricultural development; (xii) establishing a Pan African Virtual and E-University; (xiii) advancing continental cyber security, guided by the (2014) AU Convention on Cyber Security and Personal Data Protection; (xiv) establishing a Great African Museum, guided by the (2006) Charter for African Cultural Renaissance; and (xv) compiling an 
        <publ-name>Encyclopaedia Africana</publ-name>
        , to represent an authoritative and authentic resource on African history and life. In February 2024 the 37th AU summit launched the Second 10-Year Implementation Plan of Agenda 2063, or `decade of acceleration’—covering 2024-33 and focused on fostering a `prosperous, integrated, democratic, peaceful, cultured, people-driven and influential’ Africa, through the continuing pursuit of the AfCFTA and other flagship projects.
      </p>
               <p>
        In May 2013 the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="ADB.IO">AfDB</xr>
         endorsed an Africa50 Infrastructure Fund, which was to finance, in partnership with regional institutions, transformational projects with a focus on enhancing the transcontinental infrastructure.
      </p>
               <p>
        In September 2023 the AU was admitted as a permanent member of the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-OTHERORGS.IOECOFIN.002">Group of 20 (G20)</xr>
         major developed and emerging economies. A 
        
        G20-Africa Partnership initiative, including a G20 Compact with Africa—promoting private sector-led investment and development—had been initiated in June 2017.
      </p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.115" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Economic Development, Trade, Industry and Mining</heading>
               <p usage="edio">The 1991 Abuja Treaty Establishing the AEC initially envisaged that the Economic Community would be established by 2028, following a gradual six-phase process involving the co-ordination, harmonization and progressive integration of the activities of all existing and future subregional economic unions.</p>
               <p>
        The AU recognizes the following regional economic communities, or RECs, in Africa: 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="COMESA.IO">Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa (COMESA)</xr>
        , the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="WB0231.XB.TXT.73">East African Community (EAC)</xr>
        , 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="SADC.IO">Southern African Development Community (SADC)</xr>
        , 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="WB0231XB.IO.TXT.67">Communauté Economique des Etats de l'Afrique Centrale (CEEAC)</xr>
        , 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="ECOWAS.IO">Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS)</xr>
        , 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IGAD.IO">IGAD</xr>
        , and the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="WB0231XB.IO.TXT.103">Union of the Arab Maghreb</xr>
        . The inaugural meeting of the AEC took place in June 1997. In July 2007 the ninth AU Assembly adopted a Protocol on Relations between the AU and the RECs, aimed at facilitating the harmonization of policies and ensuring compliance with the schedule of the 1991 Abuja Treaty. Within the framework of the Protocol the AU Commission convenes biannual Joint Coordination Meetings comprising representatives of the AU, RECs, ECA, AfDB, NEPAD and the African Capacity Building Foundation (an AU specialized agency). In July 2023 the fifth annual Mid-Year Coordination Meeting (MYCM) was convened between the AU, African RECs, regional mechanisms and member states, with a focus on aligning and co-ordinating the implementation of the continental integration agenda.
      </p>
               <p usage="edio ewyb ass">
        A 2030 Agenda for Africa’s industrialization was launched in September 2015. In November 2014 the AU and the AfDB decided that the African Business Round Table (ABR)—comprising the chief executives of Africa’s leading corporations, and established by the AfDB in 1990 to strengthen Africa's private sector, promote intra-African trade and investment, and attract foreign investment to the continent—should become an annual meeting of the AU. An AU Extraordinary Summit on Africa’s Industrialization and Economic Diversification was convened in November 2022, in Niamey, Niger, with a focus on, 
        <i>inter alia,</i>
         aligning skills training with the developing requirements of the labour market; enhancing the continental infrastructure, especially with regard to the energy sector; mobilizing financing for the structural transformation of Africa; promoting commodity-based industrialization; and strengthening continental research and development capabilities.
      </p>
               <p usage="ass">In June 2022 the AU Commission convened an extraordinary session of the Specialized Technical Committee on Transport, Transcontinental and Interregional Infrastructure, Energy and Tourism to address impacts of the ongoing Russia-Ukraine conflict on the continental energy and infrastructure sectors.</p>
               <p>In July 2016 AU heads of state and of government launched an AU Passport policy, with the objective of facilitating the free movement of people on the continent. In January 2019 the 30th AU Assembly adopted the Protocol to the Treaty Establishing the AEC relating to the Free Movement of Persons, Rights of Residence and Right of Establishment; a draft roadmap to guide the new Protocol’s implementation was also adopted at that time. The Protocol was signed by 27 countries at the extraordinary summit held in March; by January 2024 it had been ratified by four states (Mali, Niger, Rwanda, and São Tomé and Príncipe). </p>
               <p usage="edio ewyb ass">
        The seventh edition of the joint AUC-AfDB 
        <publ-name>Africa Visa Openness Index</publ-name>
        , issued in December 2023, found that (by that year) four African states—Benin, The Gambia, Rwanda and the Seychelles—had eliminated all visa requirements for citizens of other African countries.
      </p>
               <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In February 2009 AU leaders adopted the Africa Mining Vision (AMV), which promotes the contribution of mining to sustainable local development, aiming to ensure that employees and communities benefit from industrial mining enterprises, and that priority is given to the protection of local environments. An African Minerals Development Centre, based in Maputo, Mozambique, with a mandate to implement the AMV, was inaugurated in December 2013.</p>
               <p>
        The 2023 edition of 
        <publ-name>Africa’s Development Dynamics</publ-name>
        , issued in July 2023, jointly by the AU and the OECD Development Centre, estimated that Africa required US&#8201;$1,600m. by 2030 to attain the UN Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs).
      </p>
               <!--African Growth and Opportunity Act - AGOA-->
               <p-group>
                    <heading>African Continental Free Trade Area</heading>
                    <p usage="edio">
          In January 2012 the 18th summit of AU leaders endorsed a new Framework, Roadmap and Architecture for Fast Tracking the Establishment of a Continental Free Trade Area, and an Action Plan for Boosting Intra-African Trade. The summit determined that the implementation of the AfCFTA process should follow these milestones: the finalization by 2014 of the 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-DEVTANDECCOOP.66.1">COMESA-EAC-SADC Tripartite</xr>
           FTA (the so-called TFTA was adopted in June 2015); the completion during 2012-14 of other REC FTAs (not achieved as scheduled); the consolidation of the Tripartite and other regional FTAs into the free trade area initiative during 2015-16; and the establishment of an operational AfCFTA by the end of 2017. The 2012 summit invited ECOWAS, CEEAC, CEN-SAD and the Union of the Arab Maghreb to draw inspiration from the TFTA initiative and to establish promptly a second pole of regional integration, thereby accelerating continental economic integration. The summit also recognized the need to strengthen the AU’s institutional framework for sustainable development, deeming that promoting the transition to `green’ and `blue’ economies would accelerate continental progress towards sustainable development. In June 2015 the 25th AU summit launched a series of formal negotiations on the establishment of the AfCFTA. In July 2016 AU heads of state and of government determined to establish a five-member High Level Panel (drawn from all regions) to support the fast tracking of the process. The inaugural Meeting of the AfCFTA Technical Working Groups was convened in February 2017.
        </p>
                    <p>In March 2018 the 10th extraordinary summit of AU heads of state and government, convened in the Rwandan capital Kigali, formally initiated the AfCFTA; the Agreement Establishing the AfCFTA was signed by 44 member states. It entered into force on 30 May 2019, and provided for the liberalization of 90% of tariff lines over 10 years for least developed countries (LDCs) and over five years for non-LDCs; trade in sensitive products would be liberalized over 13 years (LDCs) and 10 years (non-LDCs). The AfCFTA was declared operational in July, at an extraordinary AU summit. At that time it was decided that Ghana would host its secretariat. In December 2020 an extraordinary session of the Assembly confirmed that trading under the AfCFTA would commence on 1 January 2021. By January 2024 the accord had been signed by 54 states, and had been ratified by 47. In February 2023 AU heads of state and of government adopted AfCFTA protocols on investment and competition policy. An AfCFTA protocol on digital trade was adopted by the 37th summit in February 2024. A protocol on intellectual property was under development.</p>
                    <p>
          In support of the implementation of the AfCFTA an online African Trade Observatory (ATO) was launched in July 2019, and a new business-to-business e-commerce platform, the Africa Trade Exchange (ATEX), was initiated in May 2022. The fourth Intra-African Trade Fair was to be organized jointly by the AU Commission, AfCFTA Secretariat and 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="ECANDFINANCE.IO.1">Afreximbank</xr>
           in 2025, in Algeria.
        </p>
               </p-group>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.113" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Infrastructure and Energy</heading>
               <!--Africa Initiative on Adaptation, Loss and Damage-->
               <p>An African Energy Commission (AFREC) was inaugurated in February 2008, with the aim of increasing co-operation in energy matters between Africa and other regions. At that time a subsidiary African Electrotechnical Standardization Commission also become operational. In June 2021 the AU initiated an African Single Electricity Market (AfSEM). The AU Commission, NEPAD, the AfDB and other partners jointly lead the Africa Renewable Energy Initiative, which was launched in December 2015 to promote the installation of large-scale renewable energy capacity in Africa, with a medium-term objective of achieving the cross-continent generation of at least 300 GW of energy from renewable sources by 2030. In July 2022 the AU Executive Council adopted an African Common Position on Energy Access and Just Transition.</p>
               <p>The Bamako Convention on the Ban of the Import into Africa and the Control of Transboundary Movement and Management of Hazardous Wastes within Africa was adopted by OAU member states in 1991 and entered into force in April 1998. By January 2024 it had been signed by 35 states and ratified by 30.</p>
               <!--took out from EDIO and ASS the AU s preparations for UNCSD-->
               <p-alternates default="ASS" type="ALTERNATES">
                    <p usage="edio ass">In July 2009 the AU Assembly issued a decision endorsing the establishment of an African Agency for the Protection of Territorial and Economic Waters of African Countries. An African Charter on Maritime Security and Safety and Development in Africa (known as the Lomé Charter) was adopted in October 2016.</p>
                    <p usage="ewyb">An African Charter on Maritime Security and Safety and Development in Africa (known as the Lomé Charter) was adopted in October 2016.</p>
               </p-alternates>
               <p>In January 2012 the Executive Council endorsed an African Civil Aviation Policy. In January 2018 the 30th AU Assembly adopted a Decision on the Establishment of a Single African Air Transport Market (SAATM). By 2024 the SAATM had 34 participating states that accounted for 89% of intra-African air traffic.</p>
               <p>A Pan African E-Network Project was initiated in 2009 to advance continental connectivity. In May 2014 heads of African ICT units adopted a comprehensive Continental ICT Strategy for Africa (CISA), covering the period 2014-24, and focusing on the following themes: post and telecommunications infrastructure; capacity development; e-applications and services; enabling environment and governance; mobilization of resources and partnerships; industrialization; and research and development. A joint AU-ECA Digital Identity, Digital Trade and Digital Economy (DITE) initiative was launched in 2019. A Digital Transformation Strategy for Africa, being implemented during 2020-30, aimed to help build by 2030 a secure Digital Single Market in Africa, and to facilitate the full digital empowerment of all people on the continent.</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="IO-AU.TXT.111" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Agriculture, Rural Development, Blue Economy and Sustainable Environment</heading>
               <p>In July 2003 the second Assembly of heads of state and of government adopted the Maputo Declaration on Agriculture and Food Security in Africa, focusing on the need to revitalize the agricultural sector and to combat hunger on the continent by developing food reserves based on African production. The leaders determined to deploy policies and budgetary resources to remove current constraints on agricultural production, trade and rural development; and to implement the Comprehensive Africa Agriculture Development Programme (CAADP), as an integral programme of NEPAD. In June 2014 the 23rd Assembly of heads of state and of government, meeting in Malabo (Equatorial Guinea), extended the CAADP for the period 2014-25. The CAADP has agreed the objective of allocating at least 10% of national budgets to investment in agricultural productivity. It aims to achieve dynamic agricultural markets between African countries and regions; good participation in and access to markets by farmers; a more equitable distribution of wealth for rural populations; more equitable access to land, practical and financial resources, knowledge, information, and technology for sustainable development; development of Africa's role as a strategic player in the area of agricultural science and technology; and environmentally sound agricultural production and a culture of sustainable management of natural resources. By 2024 44 AU member states had signed CAADP compacts. During that year a further 10-year phase of the CAADP was under development, to commence in 2025. An AU Digital Agriculture Strategy and accompanying implementation plan, covering the period 2024-30, was endorsed in February 2024 by the 37th Assembly. Under the Strategy digital technology was to be harnessed to enhance the efficiency and resilience of the continent’s agricultural systems.</p>
               <p>A Revised African Convention on the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources entered into force in July 2016, and had been ratified by 17 member states at January 2024. In September 2021 the AU Commission, through the Department of Agriculture, Rural Development, Blue Economy and Sustainable Environment and the African Land Policy Centre (managed by the AU, AfDB and ECA), issued a draft continental Land Governance Strategy, which aimed to ensure more equitable land governance with secured land rights and tenure.</p>
               <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In June 2015 the AU Executive Council adopted a Regional Nutrition Strategy that covered the period 2016-25. An African Leaders for Nutrition (ALN) initiative was endorsed by AU heads of state and government in January 2018. The AU, NEPAD-AUDA and ECA prepared an African common position in advance of the UN Food Systems Summit that was convened in September 2021. Meanwhile, an Africa Food Safety Strategy was formulated. An AU High-level Food Security and Nutrition Conference was organized in October 2022. In September 2023 the 13th summit was held, in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania, of the Africa Food Systems Forum (known until 2022 as the African Green Revolution Forum).</p>
               <p>In July 2021 the AU Commission initiated a Continental Green Recovery Action Plan, to be implemented during 2021-27, with a focus on strengthening climate finance; assisting the just transition to renewable energy; pursuing nature-based solutions, with a focus on fostering biodiversity; promoting resilient agriculture; and encouraging green and resilient cities. In February 2022 the 35th AU Assembly adopted an AU Climate Change and Resilient Development Strategy and Action Plan to be implemented during the period 2022-32, and an Integrated African Strategy on Meteorology Services (that covered the period 2021-30). An African Green Stimulus Programme and AU Green Recovery Action Plan were also adopted at that time; both were focused on achieving a sustainable continental recovery from the COVID-19 pandemic. In September 2023 the AU organized, in Nairobi, Kenya, a high-level Africa Climate Summit, which was envisaged as the first in a series of planned biennial gatherings. AU leaders participating in the summit called for a revaluation of Africa’s gross domestic product, by means of a revised, fairer assessment of the continent’s `abundant natural capital’ and ecosystem services—including its vast carbon-sequestering forests (the Congo Basin equatorial rainforest is the second-largest tropical rainforest globally, after the Amazon rainforest).</p>
               <!--~ AU Biodiversity Strategy and action plan-->
               <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In June 2019 the AU and UNEP jointly organized Africa’s inaugural Wildlife Economy Summit, held at Victoria Falls, Zimbabwe, with participation by African heads of state, government ministers, academics, business people and other representatives of civil society.</p>
               <p>A Pan African Veterinary Vaccine Centre is based at Debre-Zeit, Ethiopia (and includes an AU COVID-19 Diagnostic Laboratory that was inaugurated in May 2020).</p>
               <p usage="ass">The First Conference of African Ministers of Fisheries and Aquaculture (CAMFA) was convened in September 2010, in Banjul, and CAMFA II was held in March 2014, in Entebbe, Uganda. In January 2011 the Executive Council urged member states to adopt and integrate ecosystem approaches in their national and regional fisheries management plans; to strengthen measures to address illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU) fishing; and to eliminate barriers to intraregional trade in fish and fishery products.</p>
               <p>An AU Africa Blue Economy Strategy—formulated at the instigation of African leaders who participated in a Sustainable Blue Economy Conference held in November 2018, in Nairobi, Kenya—aims to guide the development and utilization of aquatic resources in Africa, within the Agenda 2063 framework. The Strategy was endorsed in February 2020, at a side event of the AU summit meeting. It has five focal areas: fisheries, aquaculture, conservation and sustainable aquatic ecosystems; shipping and transportation, trade, ports, maritime security, safety and enforcement; coastal and maritime tourism, climate change, resilience, environment, and infrastructure; sustainable energy and mineral resources and innovative industries; and policies, governance, employment, job creation, poverty eradication, and innovative financing. In September 2023, at the inaugural Africa Climate Summit, AU leaders pledged to continue to promote a regenerative blue economy, to support the implementation of the Moroni Declaration for Ocean and Climate Action in Africa—issued in June of that year at an IUCN-supported Blue Future Ministerial Conference, held in Comoros—and to promote the IUCN-supported Great Blue Wall Initiative (focused on conserving marine and coastal ecosystems in the Western Indian Ocean).</p>
               <p-group id="AU-IO.GGW.1">
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">Great Green Wall</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">
          In December 2006 the AU adopted the Great Green Wall (GGW) for the Sahara and Sahel Initiative, comprising a set of cross-sectoral actions and interventions, such as tree planting, that were aimed at conserving and protecting natural resources; halting soil degradation and advancing desertification; reducing poverty; and increasing land productivity. The GGW was to cover 7,000 km across 22 countries in the Sahara and Sahel areas, with an initial focus on Burkina Faso, Chad, Djibouti, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Mali, Mauritania, Niger, Nigeria, Senegal and Sudan. The 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="AU-IO.GGW.22">Pan-African Agency for the GGW</xr>
           was established in 2010. In January 2021 the Food and Agriculture Organization of the UN (FAO) confirmed its ongoing commitment to the GGW; at that time the AfDB agreed to mobilize US&#8201;$6,500m. over the next five years to support several schemes aimed at advancing its implementation. 
        </p>
               </p-group>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="AU.IO.010" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Health, Humanitarian Affairs and Social Development</heading>
               <p>
        In late January 2020 the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO.AU.10">Africa Centres for Disease Control and Prevention (Africa CDC)</xr>
         activated its Incident Management System (IMS)—which is supported by the African Volunteer Health Corps (AVoHC), an entity that facilitates Africa-wide surge staffing during public health crises—to address the escalating global health crisis. On 20 March 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO.AU.10">Africa CDC</xr>
         issued an Africa Joint Continental Strategy for the COVID-19 Outbreak, with the overarching goals of preventing severe illness and death in member states, and minimizing severe social disruption and economic consequences arising from the pandemic. The Strategy was to be implemented through the Africa CDC IMS and an Africa Task Force for Novel Coronavirus, supported by an AU COVID-19 Response Fund. An Africa Medical Supplies Platform (AMSP) was launched by the AU in June to facilitate the ordering of essential medical and related inputs. Also in June the AU initiated a Partnership to Accelerate COVID-19 Testing (PACT). Meanwhile, an Africa Vaccine Strategy was launched, which aimed to secure sufficient supplies of COVID-19 vaccines and to ensure their efficient and fair distribution; a high-level Africa Vaccine Acquisition Task Team (AVATT) was established as a component of the Strategy.
      </p>
               <p>In February 2021 the AU Bureau established a Commission on African COVID-19 Response, under the leadership of South African President Cyril Ramaphosa. In April the AU and Africa CDC launched a Partnerships for African Vaccine Manufacturing (PAVM) framework, which aimed to enable the sustainable production of vaccines within Africa. AU ministers responsible for finance and the World Bank Group agreed, in June, to support an AVATT initiative to purchase and deliver vaccines for up to 400m. people across Africa, with a view to protecting 60% of the continent’s population. In September 2022 the AU Commission and Africa CDC launched a New Public Health Order initiative, which included a roadmap towards continental health security. </p>
               <p>
        In May 2023 the AU Commission and 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-GAVI.1">Gavi, the Vaccine Alliance</xr>
         concluded a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) aimed at increasing access to and accelerating the uptake of life-saving vaccines across the continent (building on the Addis Ababa Declaration on Immunization, issued in January 2017 by AU heads of state or government, which comprised commitments to increase political, technical and financial investments in immunization programmes). The AU and Africa CDC closely collaborated with 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-GAVI.1">Gavi, the Vaccine Alliance</xr>
         in the development of a new financing instrument, the African Vaccine Manufacturing Accelerator (AVMA). AVMA was endorsed in December 2023 by 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-GAVI.1">Gavi</xr>
        , and was to be formally launched in June 2024 during an event to be hosted by Africa CDC and the French Government.
      </p>
               <p>The AU promotes the eradication of endemic parasitic and infectious dis­eases and improving access to medicines. An AU African Health Strategy was being implemented during 2016-30; further long-term strategies included a Sexual and Reproductive Health and Rights Continental Policy Framework (accompanied by a Maputo Plan of Action); the Pharmaceutical Manufacturing Plan for Africa (approved in 2007); the African Regional Nutrition Strategy, covering 2015-25; the Abuja Action Plan towards the Elimination of HIV and AIDS, Malaria and Tuberculosis in Africa by 2030 (approved in 2013); the AIDS Watch Africa Strategic Framework aimed at eliminating AIDS, TB and Malaria by 2030 (endorsed in July 2017); and a Catalytic Framework to End AIDS, TB and Eliminate Malaria in Africa by 2030. A Treaty for the Establishment of the African Medicines Agency was adopted by the Assembly in February 2019. It provided for the establishment of the `AMA’ as a specialized AU body to be tasked with expanding the capacity of AU member states and regional economic commissions to regulate and improve access to safe, high-quality and effective medical products. The treaty entered into effect, having received the required 15 ratifications, in November 2021, although no agreement had been reached regarding the host country for the Agency. The first conference of the parties to the Treaty met in June 2022. An inaugural extraordinary conference session was held in November to discuss the operationalization phase of the AMA.</p>
               <p id="AU.IO.010.1" usage="edio ass mena">
        In January 2016 the AU Assembly endorsed the establishment of an African Humanitarian Agency (AfHA), as well as a Common African Position on achieving effective humanitarian action by 2025. In February 2020 the AU Assembly urged the prompt operationalization of the proposed AfHA. The first biennial 
        <publ-name>Africa Report on Disaster Risk Reduction</publ-name>
         was issued in August 2020. In November 2021 the AU supported the Eighth Africa Regional Platform for Disaster Risk Reduction and Seventh High-Level Meeting on Disaster Risk Reduction, hosted (in a hybrid format) from Nairoibi. The latter meeting adopted a near-term (2021-25) programme of action to guide the continental implementation of the Sendai Framework for Disaster Risk Reduction (which was adopted in March 2015 by the Third UN World Conference on Disaster Risk Reduction, held in Sendai City, Japan, and covers the period 2015-30). In July 2023 the inaugural policy dialogue, addressing Gender, Disaster Risk Reduction, Outbreaks, Epidemics and Food Security, was convened between the AU Commission and the African Risk Capacity.
      </p>
               <!--early warning African Union- Regional Economic Communities coordination meeting-->
               <!--pan-African Social Policy Framework (SPF)-->
               <p usage="ass">In July 2004 the Assembly adopted the Solemn Declaration on Gender Equality in Africa (SDGEA), incorporating a commitment to reporting annually on progress made towards attaining gender equality. The first conference of ministers responsible for women's affairs and gender, convened in Dakar, Senegal, in October 2005, adopted the Implementation Framework for the SDGEA, and Guidelines for Monitoring and Reporting on the SDGEA, in support of member states’ reporting responsibilities.</p>
               <p>At the January 2014 Assembly the Chairperson of the AU Commission appointed a Special Envoy for Women, Peace and Security. A fourth annual Africa Forum on Women, Peace and Security was convened in December 2023. In June 2015 the 25th AU summit adopted a common position on ending child marriage. The AU’s Saleema Initiative on Eliminating Female Genital Mutilation was launched in February 2019.</p>
               <p usage="ass">An African Committee of Experts on the Rights and Welfare of the Child was established pursuant to the African Charter on the Rights and Welfare of the Child, which was adopted by heads of state and of government in July 1990 and entered into force in November 1999. The Committee comprises 11 experts, serving in their personal capacity, who are elected by the AU Assembly. It is supported by a secretariat.</p>
               <p>In June 2020 the AU and UNICEF launched a No Name Campaign, which aimed to promote the registration of births in Africa and to ensure children’s right to a legal identity. In November, in the context of the No Name Campaign, the AU convened a videoconferenced High Level Political Dialogue on Birth Registration.</p>
               <p usage="ewyb edio ass">An African Youth Charter, which entered into force in August 2010, outlined the basic rights and responsibilities of youths (divided into four main categories: youth participation; education and skills development; sustainable livelihoods; and health and wellbeing) and detailing the obligations of member states towards young people. In January 2017 the AU Assembly adopted a roadmap on Harnessing the Demographic Dividend through Investments in Youth. The first AU Youth Envoy was appointed in November 2018.</p>
               <p usage="edio ass">A Council of the Peers was established in 2019 that was tasked with collectively championing continental arts, culture and heritage. In October 2020 a Charter for African Cultural Renaissance entered into force. A Technical and Advisory Committee of the Great Museum of Africa (GMA) is tasked with developing the GMA, an initiative focused on protecting and promoting African cultural heritage. The GMA, which was inaugurated in June 2023 at a temporary site in the Algerian capital, Algiers, was to include a Permanent Memorial of the Slave Trade.</p>
               <p>The 13th edition of the African Games, a continental sporting competition, was organized in March 2024, in Ghana.</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="AU.IO.ED.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Education, Science, Technology and Innovation </heading>
               <p>A Pan African University, headquartered in Yaoundé, Cameroon, was established in 2011, and an associated Virtual and E-University was launched in November 2019. In January 2016 AU heads of state and of government adopted a Continental Education Strategy for Africa, covering the period 2016-25. In October 2018 a Continental Strategy for Technical and Vocational Education and Training was initiated. plan of action to support an African Decade for Technical, Professional, Entrepreneurial Training and Youth Development was being implemented during 2019-2028. An AU Scientific, Technical and Research Commission is based in Abuja, and a virtual AU Network of Sciences connects 54 research institutions in Africa and Europe. In January 2016 AU heads of state and of government adopted the first African Space Policy and Strategy, as an initial step towards establishing an AU outer space programme. A statute establishing an African Space Agency entered into force in January 2019.</p>
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.112" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>Political Affairs, Peace and Security</heading>
               <p>The African Charter on Human and Peoples’ Rights, which was adopted by the OAU in 1981 and entered into force in October 1986, provided for the establishment of the African Commission on Human and Peoples' Rights. A Protocol to the Charter, establishing an African Court of Peoples’ and Human Rights, was adopted by the OAU Assembly in June 1998 and entered into force in January 2004. In February 2009 a protocol (adopted in July 2003) establishing an African Court of Justice entered into force. A Protocol on the Statute of the African Court of Justice and Human Rights, aimed at merging the African Court of Human and Peoples’ Rights and the African Court of Justice, was opened for signature in July 2008. A further Protocol, relating to the Rights of Women, was adopted by the July 2003 Maputo Assembly. An African Charter on the Rights and Welfare of the Child entered into force in November 1999. The seventh annual African Transitional Justice Forum was convened in September 2023, in Rabat, Morocco.</p>
               <p usage="ass">In May 2014 the ACHPR adopted a resolution on drafting a protocol to the African Charter on Human and Peoples’ Rights with regard to the Right to Nationality in Africa. The ACHPR subsequently advocated for action to address statelessness.</p>
               <p usage="edio ass mena">In 1964 the OAU adopted a Declaration on the Denuclearization of Africa, and in April 1996 it adopted the African Nuclear Weapons Free Zone Treaty (also known as the Pelindaba Treaty), which promotes co-operation in the peaceful uses of nuclear energy, and identifies Africa as a nuclear weapons-free zone; the Pelindaba Treaty entered into force in July 2009.</p>
               <p>The July 2002 inaugural summit meeting of AU heads of state and of government adopted a Declaration Governing Democratic Elections in Africa, providing guidelines for the conduct of national elections in member states and outlining the AU's electoral observation and monitoring role; an African Charter on Democracy, Elections and Governance entered into force in February 2012.</p>
               <p>In 2011 an African Governance Architecture was established by the Assembly, including an African Governance Platform, focused on the promotion of good governance and on strengthening democracy across the continent.</p>
               <p>
        A Convention Governing the Specific Aspects of Refugee Problems in Africa was adopted by OAU member states in 1969. It entered into force in June 1974 and had been ratified by 46 states at January 2024. The Convention promotes close co-operation with 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-UN.1443">the UN High Commissioner for Refugees</xr>
        . The AU Convention for the Protection and Assistance of IDPs in Africa (the `Kampala Convention’)—the first legally binding international treaty providing legal protection and support to people displaced within their own countries by violent conflict and natural disasters—entered into force in December 2012, and had been ratified by 33 countries by January 2024.
      </p>
               <p>A revised AU Migration Policy Framework (MPFA) and accompanying Plan of Action, covering the period 2018-30, were issued in May 2018 (superseding an original MPFA that had been adopted in 2006). The revised MPFA had the following areas of focus: border management; forced displacement; human rights of migrants; internal migration; inter-state co-operation and partnerships; irregular migration; labour migration; migration data management; and migration and development. The seventh Pan African Forum on Migration (PAFoM VII) was hosted by Rwanda, in Kigali, under AU auspices, in October 2022. In September 2023 the AU Commission helped to organize, in Addis Ababa, a High Level Dialogue on Missing Migrants (i.e. those who were reported to have died or otherwise gone missing on migration routes). A Joint Labour Migration Programme for Africa (JLMP), implemented by the AU Commission, International Labour Organization, International Organization for Migration, and ECA, was initiated in January 2015 to improve continental labour migration governance. AU efforts to combat human trafficking are guided by the 2006 Ouagadougou Action Plan to Combat Trafficking in Human Beings.</p>
               <p>An AU Convention on Preventing and Combating Corruption entered into force in August 2006, and in May 2009 an associated AU Advisory Board on Corruption was inaugurated. An AU Convention on Cyber Security and Personal Data Protection was adopted in June 2014, and by January 2024 had 15 states parties. In June 2021 the AU Commission, supported by the Council of Europe, organized the second African Cybercrime Forum, in Addis Ababa. (The first had been convened in October 2018.)</p>
               <p usage="edio">
        In October 2013 an extraordinary summit of the AU Assembly, convened on the theme `Africa’s relationship with the International Criminal Court’, determined that—in order to safeguard the constitutional order, stability and integrity of member states—no trial proceedings ought to be commenced or continued before any international court or tribunal against any serving AU head of state or of government, or against anybody acting in such capacity, during her or his term of office. The summit specifically requested the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="INTCC.IO">Court</xr>
         to defer until after the expiry of their terms of office the indictments that were issued in 2011 against the serving President of Kenya, Uhuru Muigai Kenyatta, and his Vice-President, William Samoei Ruto, in relation to violent unrest that followed the December 2007 presidential elections there. The summit decided to convene an Executive Council Contact Group to engage with the UN Security Council on all concerns of the AU regarding its relationship with the 
        <xr pageref="N" ref="INTCC.IO">Court</xr>
        , including the deferral of the Kenyan cases, and the arrest warrant issued by the Court in 2009 against former President Omar al-Bashir of Sudan, concerning his alleged responsibility for the perpetration of war crimes in Darfur. (The Kenyan cases were withdrawn in early 2016.)
      </p>
               <p usage="ass">In January 2017 the 28th AU Assembly adopted a non-binding decision that supported a strategy of collective African withdrawal from the International Criminal Court. In May, with a view to strengthening relations with Africa, the Court, with support from the Swiss Government, convened (in Dakar) a high-level conference on `Capacity-building with regard to African judicial systems through effective and dynamic complementarity and co-operation with the International Criminal Court’. In March 2018 a Nigerian national was elected as President of the Court.</p>
               <!--if the Court does not reform its procedures?-->
               <!--Possible section to be added above to match ECOSOCC section. AU stance on leaders kept in power through constitutional changes -->
               <p usage="ass mena">The Protocol to the Constitutive Act of the African Union Relating to the Establishment of the Peace and Security Council, adopted by the inaugural AU summit of heads of state and of government in July 2002, entered into force in December 2003, superseding the 1993 Cairo Declaration on the OAU Mechanism for Conflict Prevention, Management and Resolution. The Protocol provides for the development of a collective peace and security framework (known as the African Peace and Security Architecture—APSA). This includes a Peace and Security Council, operational at the levels of heads of state and of government, ministers responsible for foreign affairs, and permanent representatives, to be supported by a five-member advis­ory Panel of the Wise, a Continental Early Warning System, an African Standby Force (ASF) and a Peace Fund. In February 2004 the Assembly adopted a Common African Defence and Security Policy (CADSP). A Network of African Women in Conflict Prevention and Mediation (FemWise-Africa)—a subsidiary mechanism of the Panel of the Wise—was formally endorsed in July 2017 by AU heads of state and of government.</p>
               <p>The activities of the AU Peace and Security Council include early warning and preventive diplomacy; peacemaking mediation; peace support operations and intervention; peacebuilding activities and post-conflict reconstruction; and humanitarian action and disaster management. The Council is tasked with implementing the common defence policy of the Union, and ensuring the implementation of the 1999 OAU Convention on the Prevention and Combating of Terrorism (under which signatory states were to exchange information and refrain from granting asylum to terrorists).</p>
               <p>The AU Non-Aggression and Common Defence Pact, which entered into force in December 2009, stipulates measures aimed at preventing and at peacefully resolving inter- and intra-state conflicts. The Pact states that an act, or threat, of aggression against an individual member state affects all member states.</p>
               <p>The African Centre for the Study and Research on Terrorism (ACSRT) and the Committee of Intelligence and Security Services in Africa (CISSA) were both established in 2004. In 2014 the 23rd Assembly adopted an AU Convention on Cross-Border Cooperation, referred to as the Niamey Convention. An AU Mechanism for Police Cooperation (AFRIPOL), comprising member states’ chiefs of police, was launched in May 2017. In December 2019 an AU Ministerial Meeting adopted the Bamako Declaration on Access to Natural Resources and Conflicts between Communities. African Youth Ambassadors for Peace represent five continental regions.</p>
               <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In December 2000 OAU heads of state and of government adopted the Bamako Declaration, concerned with arresting the circulation of small arms and light weapons (SALW) within the continent. It was envisaged that the Central African Convention for the Control of SALW, their Ammunition, Parts and Components that can be used for their Manufacture, Repair or Assembly (Kinshasa Convention), which was adopted by Central African states in April 2010 and entered into force in February 2017, would contribute to the AU’s SALW control capacity. In November 2016 the Peace and Security Council adopted an AU Master Roadmap on Practical Steps to Silence the Guns in Africa. In February 2020 the Assembly requested the AU Commission to integrate child protection into the Silencing the Guns agenda. In December of that year the 14th extraordinary session of the AU Assembly issued the Johannesburg Declaration on Silencing the Guns, which extended the timeframe of the Master Roadmap until 2030.</p>
               <p>In May 2022 the 16th extraordinary session of the Assembly, convened in Malabo (Equatorial Guinea) issued a Declaration on Terrorism and Unconstitutional Changes of Government, which noted the negative impacts across the continent of a resurgence of unconstitutional changes of government, the expanding threat of terrorism and violent extremism, a proliferation of armed groups, continuing transnational crime, and an influx of foreign terrorist fighters and of private military companies and mercenaries (notably, the Wagner Goup—a Russian private paramilitary and security contractor). It was noted that deficits in governance, and terrorism and violent extremism were being compounded by the impacts of climate change, and that terrorist groupings were self-funding through the exploitation of continental natural resources. The Assembly determined to scale up the implementation of all relevant AU instruments and decisions, and to accelerate the full operationalizion of the ASF. External actors were urged to cease supporting terrorist groups across the continent. The Assembly determined to develop a comprehensive continental strategic plan of action focused on countering terrorism in Africa, and to strengthen the capacity of the AU Commission and of relevant AU agencies.</p>
               <p>An AU Policy on Post-Conflict Reconstruction and Development has been pursued since 2006. In December 2021 a Cairo (Egypt)-based AU Centre for Post-conflict Reconstruction and Development (PCRD) was inaugurated.</p>
               <p usage="edio mena">In January 2018 the 30th AU Assembly requested Morocco to permit the return of an AU Observer Mission to Laayoune (Western Sahara), and to admit independent human rights monitors to the area. The Assembly also called for joint UN-AU facilitated negotiations on the organization of a free and fair referendum to determine the future of Western Sahara. (The Moroccan authorities had expelled the AU Observer Mission in March 2016, with UN international civilian staff, following an incident in which the UN Secretary-General had referred to Morocco’s presence in Western Sahara as an `occupation’.) In July 2018 the 31st AU Assembly, in a change of direction on the matter, decided to decelerate the AU’s own peace activities in Western Sahara (which had been deemed by Morocco as `biased’), and to place increased focus on supporting—through the establishment of a Troika of heads of state—the ongoing UN-led political process there.</p>
               <p usage="ass">In November 2019 the AU and NATO concluded an agreement (updating a previous accord) that was to guide continuing mutual practical and political co-operation, with a focus on developing logistical, operational and capacity-building support.</p>
               <p>In late December 2023 the UN Security Council approved a resolution (2719) to extend funding, on a case-by-case basis, to AU-led peace and security missions.</p>
               <p-group>
                    <heading>AU Peace Fund</heading>
                    <p>In July 2016 the AU Assembly agreed on an initial endowment and subsequent 0.2% import levy to support the activities of the Peace Fund, which included three thematic support windows (on mediation and preventive diplomacy, institutional capacity and peace support operations), as well as a Crisis Reserve Facility. A Board of Trustees was appointed in November 2018, when the Fund was officially inaugurated. In May 2023 the Board of Trustees recommended that the endowment of the Crisis Reserve Facility should be doubled from US&#8201;$5m. to $10m. in 2023/24, to enable effective interventions to secure peace and security across the continent. In 2023 the Fund focused on supporting the AU Transition Mission in Somalia; interventions in the political crisis in Sudan; and initiatives in East African Community member states.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading>African Standby Force (ASF)</heading>
                    <p>An extraordinary AU summit meeting, convened in Sirte, in February 2004, adopted a declaration approving the establishment of the multi­national ASF, which was to comprise rapidly deployable multidimensional military, police and civilian capabilities, and was to be mandated to undertake observation, monitoring and other peace support missions; to deploy in member states as required to prevent the resurgence or escalation of violence; to intervene as required to restore stability; to conduct post-conflict disarmament and demob­ilization and other peacebuilding activities; and to provide emergency ­hu­manitarian assistance. The Force was to be drawn from five regional brigades: the North African Regional Capability (NARC), the Eastern African Standby Force (EASF), the Force Multinationale de l’Afrique Centrale (FOMAC), the SADC Standby Brigade (SADCBRIG) and ECOWAS Standby Force (ESF). The NARC and the EASF Coordination Mechanism (EASFCOM) maintain liaison offices at the AU’s headquarters.</p>
                    <p>In January 2014 AU leaders endorsed the creation of an interim African Capacity for Immediate Response to Crises (ACIRC), to be deployed as a continental rapid reaction force in emergency situations, pending the ASF’s full operationalization (which required substantial additional financing). In July 2016 the 27th AU summit authorized the establishment of a donor-funded AU Special Fund for Prevention and Combating of Terrorism and Violent Extremism. An ASF Continental Logistics Base was inaugurated in Douala, Cameroon, in January 2018.</p>
               </p-group>
               <!--ASS only entry on EASF &c.. paragraph on AMIB and ONUB removed from ASS-->
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass">Boko Haram</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">In January 2015 the AU Assembly welcomed ongoing efforts by the Lake Chad Basin Commission (LCBC), and Benin, to eliminate the terrorist grouping Jama'atu Ahlus Sunnah lid Da'awati wal Jihad (`Boko Haram’). In March Boko Haram pledged allegiance to Islamic State, formally becoming Islamic State's West Africa Province—ISWAP. However, a splinter faction subsequently re-identified as Boko Haram. In that month the Peace and Security Council authorized the deployment of a Multinational Joint Task Force, under the operational control of the Commission, which was to combat Boko Haram in north-eastern Nigeria and surrounding border regions. In May 2016 the AU convened in Abuja a Second Regional Security Meeting, at which US&#8201;$250m. was raised to fund operations against the group. In February 2017 the AU Commissioner for Peace and Security and Chad’s Minister of Public Security and Immigration issued a joint communiqué that addressed means—such as temporary detention, deradicalization and community reintegration—of managing former members of Boko Haram. In late August 2018 an AU-LCBC ministerial conference, held in Abuja, adopted a Regional Stabilization, Recovery and Resilience Strategy for Areas Affected by Boko Haram in the Lake Chad Basin Region. The Strategy was endorsed in December by the AU Peace and Security Council. A Regional Stabilization Facility for Lake Chad was launched by the UN Development Programme in July 2019, in support of the initiative. In July 2021 the Peace and Security Council stated concern over the protracted insecurity in the region, including continuing attacks by non-state actors, abductions of schoolchildren, and the impacts of climate change on many people’s livelihoods (for example the impacts on fish production of drying in Lake Chad, and the degradation of pasturelands). The Council noted that the reported death in May of the Boko Haram terrorist leader Abubakar Shekau was prompting a consolidation of the activities of ISWAP.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">Burkina Faso</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In late January 2022 the Chairperson of the AU Commission strongly condemned a military coup that had overthrown the democratically elected President of Burkina Faso, Roch Marc Christian Kaboré. Soon afterwards Burkina Faso was suspended from the AU, pending the restoration of constitutional order. The AU pledged to co-operate closely with ECOWAS in seeking a solution to the crisis. In mid-February an interim military junta-appointed president, Lt-Col Paul-Henri Sandaogo Damiba, was inaugurated. A charter detailing a three-year schedule of transition to democratic elections was issued at the beginning of March, and an interim Prime Minister designated soon afterwards. In mid-2022, following the appointment of an ECOWAS Mediator for Burkina Faso, a new timetable was announced, whereby the transition to constitutional rule would be completed in mid-2024. On 30 September 2022 the Chairperson of the AU Commission unequivocally condemned a new seizure of power in Burkina Faso, by Capt. Ibrahim Traoré. Traoré, who cited a worsening security situation as the cause of the coup, subsequently committed to the ongoing timetable for a return to constitutional rule. In January 2024 the Chairperson of the AU Commission stated regret over an announcement by Burkina Faso, Mali and Niger of their intention to withdraw from ECOWAS.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ass">Central African Republic (CAR)</heading>
                    <p usage="ass">In July 2017 the AU Commission endorsed an African Initiative for Peace and National Reconciliation in the CAR and supporting Roadmap, which were to be led jointly by the AU, CEEAC and the International Conference on the Great Lakes Region (ICGLR), with the aim of promoting dialogue between the CAR authorities and militant groupings, and achieving long-term national disarmament. In February 2019, after a year of negotiations within the context of the African Initiative, 14 rebel groups and the Government signed, under AU auspices, the Political Agreement for Peace and Reconciliation in the CAR (PAPR-CAR). Representatives of the AU Peace and Security Council and of the Political and Security Committee of the EU visited the CAR in the following month to support the implementation of the new Political Agreement. In February 2020 the AU Assembly urged all CAR stakeholders to ensure that a pending general election should be organized in strict compliance with the February 2019 PAPR-CAR and with domestic CAR laws. President Faustin Touadéra was commended for efforts aimed at promoting inclusive consensus, and in particular for instituting a Peace Agreement-focused dialogue with former national heads of state. An MOU was concluded in mid-2020 between a new AU Military Observers Mission to the CAR (MOUACA) and MINUSCA. Touadéra was re-elected in late December 2020, winning an outright majority at the first round of the presidential poll. In June 2021 the AU Commissioner for Political Affairs, Peace and Security, the UN Under-Secretary-General for Peace Operations, and representatives of CEEAC and the EU collectively visited Bangui with a view to promoting a credible and inclusive political dialogue to consolidate and advance the peace process. In July the Peace and Security Council stated deep concern over worsening insecurity in the CAR, and urged armed groups that had withdrawn from the 2019 PAPR-CAR unconditionally to cease all hostilities and to rejoin the peace process. The Council urged the CAR Government to take all necessary steps to prevent the illegal exploitation of national mineral resources, and to improve the delivery of basic public services to the people of the country. In mid-October 2021 the UN Security Council welcomed the announcement of a ceasefire by Touadéra, following the adoption by the ICGLR in the previous month of a roadmap aimed at achieving peace in the CAR. A Republican Dialogue on reconciliation, convened in March 2022, was boycotted by most opposition representatives. In June 2023 the AU Peace and Security Council stated deep concern over disagreement among CAR stakeholders concerning the organization of a pending constitutional referendum; a peaceful resolution of differences was urged. Concern was also expressed over the deteriorating humanitarian situation in the CAR, impacted by the ongoing conflict in Sudan and by the activities of armed non-state groupings. The full removal of the arms embargo imposed on the CAR was urged. (At the referendum, held to plan at the end of July, 95.3% of votes cast favoured the new Constitution.)</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">Chad</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In April 2021 the AU Peace and Security Council stated `grave concern’ and urged an end to military rule in Chad, following the killing by rebels of President Idriss Déby, and decision by military leaders that Déby's son, Gen. Mahamat Déby Itno, would head a military council for 18 months prior to the organization of national elections. In October 2022 the transition period was extended by a further 24 months. In November the AU Peace and Security Council requested the AU Commission to dispatch the organization’s Panel of the Wise to assess developments in Chad and to consult with national stakeholders. In May 2023 the Panel briefed the Council on its findings; the Council subsequently emphasized that members of the national transitional regime should not be permitted to participate in the planned democratic elections. A constitutional referendum was in Chad in December. In February 2024 the 37th AU summit gave consideration to the need to reverse the environmental degradation of Lake Chad, which, owing to over-exploitation and impacts of climate change, had lost considerable volume in recent decades (exacerbating local conflicts among herders and farmers).</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">DRC</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">
          In late June 2023 a quadripartite summit was convened under AU auspices, in Luanda, Angola, to address the harmonization of ongoing interventions in the DRC, with participation by the 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="WB0231XB.IO.TXT.73">EAC</xr>
          , 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="SADC.IO">SADC</xr>
          , 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="WB0231XD.IO.TXT.28.2">ICGLR</xr>
          , and 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="WB0231XB.IO.TXT.67">CEEAC</xr>
           (the `Quadripartite Platform’). The summit demanded the immediate and unconditional withdrawal of all illegal armed groups from occupied territories in the DRC, with particular reference to the March 23 Movement (M23), Allied Democratic Forces, and Forces démocratiques de libération du Rwanda (FDLR); for the creation of humanitarian corridors; and for the establishment of a new AU-co-ordinated Multilevel Coordination Working Group—to comprise representatives of the DRC, Rwanda and UN, and the Chairs of the EAC, ICGLR, SADC and CEEAC. The Working Group was to have a political, diplomatic, military, socio-economic and humanitarian focus, and was to facilitate exchange of information, to foster coherence. The Quadripartite Platform member organizations were asked to report on a quarterly basis to the AU Peace and Security Council, and the AU Commission was requested to call a meeting of the Quadripartite Platform chiefs of defence, with a view to co-ordinating (in agreement with the DRC authorities) ongoing and planned military deployments in eastern DRC. A Meeting of Chiefs of Defence of the Quadripartite was convened, against under AU auspices, in October, in Addis Ababa. It requested the AU immediately to operationalize a Multilevel Coordination Working Group, with representation from all participating organizations, the UN, and the DRC and Rwanda. The Group was to organize a biannual meeting of quadripartite Chiefs of Defence, and a quarterly gathering of technical military experts.
        </p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass">Eswatini</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">At the beginning of July 2021 the Chairperson of the AU Commission stated deep concern over an escalating political and security crisis in Eswatini, where pro-democracy demonstrations were being organized to demand political reforms to the national system of absolute monarchy. Numerous incidents of violent unrest had been reported, and by that time at least 20 activists were believed by the international human rights organization Amnesty International to have been killed (and a further 150 to have been injured) by the national security forces. Curfews had been imposed and schools suspended by the national authorities, with a view to controlling the unrest. The Chairperson strongly condemned all related fatalities and destruction of property. He called for immediate action to protect citizens, and for all national stakeholders to pursue constructive dialogue towards a peaceful resolution of the situation. An AU Observer Mission sent to observe a general election that was held in Eswatini in late September 2023 found it to have been conducted in a generally peaceful atmosphere.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass ewyb">Ethiopia</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">An AU Commission of Inquiry on Tigray was initiated in mid-June 2021, under the auspices of the African Commission on Human and People’s Rights, with a mandate to investigate violations of international human rights law and international humanitarian law that had allegedly been perpetrated during the civil conflict that had prevailed in Tigray (northern Ethiopia) since November 2020. In late June 2021 the Chairperson welcomed the Ethiopian Federal Government’s declaration of a humanitarian ceasefire in Tigray. In August the Chairperson appointed Chief Obasanjo as AU High Representative for the Horn of Africa region. The Chairperson welcomed the declaration of an indefinite humanitarian truce in the region, announced by the Ethiopian authorities in March 2022, and urged his High Representative to continue efforts to secure a permanent ceasefire and a political settlement to the conflict. In early October the Chairperson of the AU Commission welcomed agreement by the Ethiopian Prime Minister, Dr Abiy Ahmed, and the Tigrayan leadership to participate in high-level peace talks. The talks, held under AU auspices and mediated by a panel of eminent Africans, were initiated later in that month in Pretoria, South Africa, and culminated on 2 November in the signing of a peace accord. In early January 2024 the Chairperson of the AU Commission appealed for calm as tensions mounted between Ethiopia and Somalia, following the conclusion by Ethiopia and Somalia’s separatist region of Somaliland, on 1 January, of a controversial accord under which Ethiopia was to be granted maritime access to the Red Sea port of Berbera for 50 years, in return for de facto formal recognition of Somaliland’s regime.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">Gabon</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">On 30 August 2023 the Chairperson of the AU Commission stated great concern at the situation in Gabon, strongly condemning the overthrow by the military of President Ali Bongo Ondimba, the dissolution of all institutions of state, and nullification (citing fraud) of the results of a recent election in which 64.3% of the votes cast had been allocated to Bongo (who was by then being held under house arrest). A son of the deposed president, also in detention, was accused by the coup leaders of treason. All political, civil and military actors were urged by the AU Commission Chairperson to prioritize peaceful political pathways, and to facilitate a swift return to constitutional order. On 31 August the AU’s Peace and Security Council suspended Gabon’s participation in the activities of the organization. Bongo was released from house arrest, on health grounds, in early September.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass mena">Grand Ethiopian Renaissance Dam (GERD)</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass mena">In mid-2020 the Chairperson of the AU Assembly determined to lead a consultation process aimed at resolving a longstanding dispute concerning Ethiopia’s construction of the GERD—on the Blue Nile, the River Nile’s main tributory—and its impacts, including potential water losses, on Egypt and Sudan (both downstream Nile countries). The resulting inaugural meeting of the AU Bureau to review progress in Trilateral Negotiations on the GERD was convened in late June. Several meetings were subsequently held, but the negotiations process eventually stalled, with Egypt and Sudan reportedly seeking a legally binding international accord, providing a formal mechanism to resolve future disputes, and Ethiopia unilaterally advocating for a non-binding approach. In September the UN Security Council issued a statement that urged the resumption of constructive negotiations under AU auspices. Electricity production from the GERD commenced in February 2022, and was augmented in August. Intergovernmental talks on the situation were revived in August 2023. In January 2024 final phase of the operationalization of the GERD was launched.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass ewyb">Guinea</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass ewyb">On 10 September 2021 the AU suspended Guinea, following the overthrow in a military coup of that country’s longstanding President Alpha Condé and dissolution of the Guinean Government and of the national Constitution—which, in 2020, against a background of widespread opposition, had been revised to enable Condé to serve a third term of office.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio mena">Libya</heading>
                    <p usage="edio mena">In May 2014 the AU Peace and Security Council issued a statement expressing deep concern about violent insecurity emerging from the ongoing political transition process in Libya. A Special Envoy was appointed, at the request of the Council, in June. An International Contact Group for Libya, established by the AU, held its inaugural meeting in December. In January 2015 the Chairperson of the AU Commission welcomed the initiation of a UN-mediated national political dialogue in Libya. In October the participants in the dialogue finalized a political agreement on establishing a Government of National Accord. A majority of the participants in the dialogue formally adopted the Libyan Political Agreement at a gathering convened in mid-December, in Skhirat, Morocco. In October the AU High Representative for Libya, the Special Representative of the UN Secretary-General, and the Secretary-General of the League of Arab States (Arab League) announced the formation of a Troika aimed at advancing the ongoing political process. This was superseded in March 2017 by the establishment of an AU-UN-Arab League-EU Quartet formation as a joint framework for co-ordinating efforts to address the Libyan crisis (see under the UN Support Mission in Libya for further details). In November the Chairperson of the AU Commission condemned the reported auctioning of African migrants in Tripoli by international criminal networks, and urged the African Commission on Human and Peoples’ Rights to support an investigation that the Libyan authorities had opened into the allegations.</p>
                    <p usage="edio mena">In January 2018 the 30th AU Assembly reiterated deep concern over the continuing political impasse and unstable security situation in Libya. The Assembly requested the AU Commission to re-launch, in close co-operation with the UN, the work of the International Contact Group on Libya. The AU High Representative for Libya and AU High-Level Committee on Libya (established in March 2011) continued to hold regular consultations with Libyan political stakeholders. In July 2018 the AU Chairperson stated concern over a recent escalation of conflict in Libya’s `oil crescent’ area. In April 2019 the AU Commission Chairperson, accompanied by several AU Commission officials, held discussions in Tripoli with Libyan stakeholders, including the Chairman of the Presidential Council of Libya, the Prime Minister of the GNA, and the Commander of the Libyan National Army. In the following month the third AU-UN Annual Conference emphasized the need for the UN and regional organizations to support a single roadmap for a political resolution in Libya.</p>
                    <p usage="edio mena">In July 2019 the AU Peace and Security Council stated grave concern over the situation in Libya, and in particular over the plight of African migrants in camps and detention facilities there. It condemned the recent bomb attack against the Tajoura Detention Centre, near Tripoli, that had caused 53 fatalities and severely injured several hundred people, and called for the perpetrators to be held accountable. An extraordinary session of the ACHPR, meanwhile, issued a resolution that condemned lethal fighting and attacks in Libya, including attacks on migrants and refugees; called on the parties to the conflict to cease such attacks; called on the international community to prioritize the protection of the human rights of civilians, migrants and refugees; and urged all parties to focus on dialogue.</p>
                    <p usage="edio mena">The AU participates, with the Arab League, EU, UN and several partner countries, in the International Follow-Up Committee on Libya, which was established to pursue the outcome of the International Conference on Libya that had been held in Berlin, Germany, in February 2020. In August the Chairperson of the AU Assembly welcomed commitments to a ceasefire made by the parties to the Libyan conflict; an agreement on a ceasefire was signed on 23 October. In February 2021 the AU Chairperson commended the election by a UN-facilitated inclusive Libyan Political Dialogue Forum (LPDF, initiated in October 2020) of a unified interim government, to guide Libya towards presidential and legislative elections that were scheduled to be held on 24 December. In mid-March he welcomed the installation of the interim administration. At the end of August the AU Commissioner for Political Affairs, Peace and Security, the Arab League Secretary-General, the UN Special Envoy for Libya, and the foreign ministers of Algeria, Chad, Egypt, Libya, Niger, Nigeria, Sudan and Tunisia, participating in a `Libya’s neighbours’ conference, decided to send a ministerial delegation to Libya to contact all stakeholders, with a view to pursuing a political resolution of continuing tensions. The planned elections were postponed in December, in the absence of an agreed legal framework. The Chairperson of the AU Commission stated deep concern in late August 2022 over the ongoing build-up of military forces and eruption of violent clashes in Tripoli. In July 2023 the head of the AU High-Level Committee on Libya organized an AU-Libya meeting that gave consideration to establishing a preparatory committee to organize a national conference on reconciliation. A summit meeting of the AU High-Level Committee on Libya that was convened in February 2024, in Brazzaville, Republic of the Congo, with UN and Arab League representation, urged Libya’s Presidential Council to establish promptly a National Commission for Reconciliation, and commended the planned organization of (as previously proposed) a National Reconciliation Conference, to be held in late April, in Sirte. The Committee reiterated to all external actors that they should refrain from interfering in the internal affairs of Libya, and called on all mercenaries and foreign fighters to withdraw. In March, at a meeting organized by the Arab League, the heads of Libya’s Presidential Council, High State Council and the Speaker of the House of Representatives agreed on the need to hold national elections, and decided to form a technical committee to address outstanding controversial issues.</p>
                    <p usage="edio mena">An AU-EU-UN Tripartite Taskforce on the Situation of Migrants and Refugees in Libya was initiated in early 2022. Meeting in March 2023 the Taskforce determined to strengthen efforts to support the development of non-discriminatory legal and policy frameworks for migrants and refugees in that country, and urged the Libyan authorities to end arbitrary detention of migrants and refugees. The Taskforce agreed to enhance support for voluntary humanitarian returns from Libya.</p>
                    <!--~ www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-51293355-->
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ass">Lord’s Resistance Army</heading>
                    <p usage="ass">The Regional Cooperation Initiative for the Elimination of the Lord’s Resistance Army (AU RCI-LRA) was authorized by the Peace and Security Council in November 2011, and officially launched in March 2012, comprising: a Joint Coordination Mechanism, based in Bangui, CAR, and chaired by the AU Commissioner for Peace and Security, with participation by the ministers responsible for defence of LRA-affected countries (i.e. Uganda, the CAR, the DRC and South Sudan), and responsibility for strategic co-ordination with all affected states and actors; a Regional Task Force (AU RTF), with a troop ceiling of 5,000, comprising national contingents from LRA-affected countries; and a Joint Operations Centre, reporting to the RTF Commander. Actions by the AU RCI-LRA reportedly achieved the removal of several LRA commanders, as well as a downward turn in the numbers of LRA abductions and killings, and a significant increase in the number of defections from the rebel grouping. In January 2015 the AU RCI-LRA transferred Dominic Ongwen, a senior LRA commander who had been indicted by the International Criminal Court on charges relating to crimes against humanity, to the custody of the CAR authorities; he was subsequently placed in the custody of the Court. In June 2016 the Ugandan Government announced that it intended to implement a phased withdrawal of Uganda’s 2,500 troops from the AU RTF (which at November 2015 comprised 3,085 troops—only around three-fifths of its envisaged configuration). In mid-2016 an AU-UN-EU-US joint technical assessment mission reported that the LRA remained an active threat, and that insecurity in the region was amplified by the presence of other militia—including the ex-Séléka faction (opposed to the CAR Government) and the Janjaweed (active in western Sudan and eastern Chad). It urged the renewal of the mandate of US special forces, which had been deployed to provide logistical support to the AU RTF. In April 2017, however, when the withdrawal of Ugandan forces commenced, the US Administration terminated US engagement against the LRA. Meanwhile, South Sudan indicated that it would no longer host the AU RTF headquarters (hitherto based in Yambio): therefore, they relocated to Koboko, Uganda, in July. In 2022 it was reported that the LRA comprised between 200-1,000 combatants in disparate groupings, largely funded through the smuggling of arms and ivory.</p>
                    <!--Uganda contingent - Dec. Postponements. UN: more than 100,000 people were killed by the LRA across several countries and regions, and between 60,000 and 100,000 children were abducted (many used as child soldiers). More than 1m. people displaced as a direct consequence of LRA attacks-->
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass ewyb">Mali</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass ewyb">In mid-August 2020 the AU Chairperson strongly condemned the removal of Mali’s democratically elected Government by a military coup. Pending the restoration of constitutional order, Mali was suspended by the Peace and Security Council from participation in AU processes. The Council demanded the release of President Ibrahim Boubacar Keïta and Prime Minister Boubou Cisse and the other forcibly detained government officials. In late August Keïta left Mali to receive medical treatment in the United Arab Emirates. In mid-September the new military leadership determined that an 18-month transitional government, led by a civilian president, would be established pending new national elections. A charter to govern the transition over the next 18 months was issued at the beginning of October (this extended an amnesty to the leaders of the coup); the AU consequently reversed Mali’s suspension. In mid-November the AU Chairperson visited Mali and met the Malian transitional leadership and senior UN presence. The inaugural meeting of a Transition Support Group on Mali (GST-Mali)—with participation by the AU, ECOWAS, the UN Multidimensional Stabilization Mission in Mali, and other partners—was convened at the end of November, in Bamako. A second GST-Mali meeting took place in March 2021. In late May the AU and other GST-Mali participants stated deep concern at the recent arrest by the Malian military of members of the transitional authorities and demanded their immediate release. Shortly afterwards the interim President and premier were forced to resign their posts (while continuing to be detained under house arrest). On 1 June the Peace and Security Council once again suspended Mali’s AU membership, and called on the Malian military `urgently and unconditionally’ to return to their barracks and to cease interfering in the national political process. The Council warned that, otherwise, punitive sanctions would be imposed. In mid-2022 a new timetable was announced, under which a referendum on a proposed new Constitution and legislative elections would be organized during 2023, and a presidential poll would be held in February 2024. The third meeting of the GST-Mali, held in early September 2022, welcomed the lifting of economic and financial sanctions that had been imposed on Mali by ECOWAS. In May 2023 the Chairperson of the AU Commission welcomed an announcement by the Malian authorities that the planned constitutional referendum would be held on 18 June; at the poll, 97% of votes cast (on a turnout of 39.4%) favoured the proposed changes. The legislative and presidential elections were, however, postponed.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass">Mauritius</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">In February 2021 the 34th AU Assembly adopted a decision that called on member states to support all regional, international and intergovernmental efforts to enable Mauritius to assert its sovereignty over the Chagos Archipelago, pursuant to an Advisory Opinion issued in February 2019 by the International Court of Justice (ICJ) relating to the legal consequences of the separation of the Chagos Archipelago from Mauritius in 1965 to form the British Indian Ocean Territory. The ICJ had found that the archipelago had been, and remained, unlawfully occupied by the United Kingdom. Its ruling had been endorsed in May 2019 by the UN General Assembly, which had adopted a (non-binding) resolution setting a deadline of 22 November 2019, by which the UK ought to relinquish sovereignty of the islands and return them to Mauritius. The UK, however, had stated that it would continue to administer the territory, and had ignored the deadline. The 34th AU Assembly welcomed a judgment issued in late January 2021 by the International Tribunal for the Law of the Sea (ITLOS), which also found that Mauritius had sovereignty over the Chagos Archipelago, and condemned the continued occupation of the islands by the UK.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass">Mozambique</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">At the end of March 2021 the Chairperson of the AU Commission strongly condemned terrorist attacks in Mozambique’s Cabo Delgado region (perpetrated by Ahl al-Sunna Wal-Jama’a, associated with Islamic State Central Africa Province), and particularly recent atrocities in the vicinity of the coastal town of Palma. He stated utmost concern at the presence of international terrorist groups in southern Africa, and called for a co-ordinated regional and international response.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">Niger</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In late July 2023 the Chairperson of the AU Commission strongly condemned a coup conducted in Niger by members of the Nigerien Presidential Guard, under the leadership of General Abdourahmane 'Omar' Tchiani, against the (in 2021) democratically elected President, Mahmoud Bazoum. The Chairperson urged the perpetrators immediately to halt their actions. An extraordinary meeting of the Peace and Security Council that was convened soon afterwards issued a 15-day ultimatum to the perpetrators to reinstate President Bazoum and to restore constitutional order, on pain of the imposition of punitive sanctions. The Council reiterated its zero tolerance for unconstitutional changes of government. On 11 August the Chairperson of the AU Commission stated his strong support for a recent decision by the ECOWAS Authority to activate the ESF, with a view to deploying it to Niger to restore constitutional order. The Nigerien military leadership was urged to halt the escalation of tensions with ECOWAS, including by releasing President Bazoum and other associated detainees. Deep concern was expressed at the reportedly poor conditions in which Bazoum was being held. On 22 August the AU’s Peace and Security Council agreed to suspend Niger’s membership of the AU with immediate effect.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass">Nouakchott Process</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">In December 2014 the AU Chairperson convened the inaugural summit of countries—Algeria, Burkina Faso, Chad, Côte d'Ivoire, Libya, Mali, Mauritania and Senegal—participating in the so-called Nouakchott Process on the Enhancement of Security Co-operation and the Operationalization of the APSA in the Sahelo-Saharan Region. In April 2017 the AU Peace and Security Council endorsed the strategic concept of operations, and deployment, of a joint counter-terrorism force—the Force conjointe du G5 Sahel (FC-G5S)—which was tasked with combating violent extremist groups operating in the common space of the member states of the G5 Sahel grouping. The deployment of the FC-G5S—to comprise up to 5,000 military and police personnel—was endorsed by the UN Security Council in June; in December the Council authorized the Multidimensional Integrated Stabilization Mission in Mali to provide the FC-G5S with logistical and operational support. In January 2020, at a summit attended in Pau, France, by the G5 Sahel heads of state, President Emmanuel Macron of France and the UN Secretary-General, a Niamey, Niger-based joint command mechanism was established for the FC-G5S and French Opération Barkhane (deployed in the region to support action against terrorist insurgencies). The strategic concept of operations of the FC-G5S was revised at that time. In February the AU Assembly—expressing deep concern over continuing incidents in the Sahel region of terrorism, banditry, cross-border crime and of all forms of trafficking—emphasized the need to support through enhanced financing ECOWAS-led and other regional initiatives aimed at securing peace. In June 2021 the Chairperson of the AU Commission condemned a terrorist attack which caused more than 130 fatalities in Solhan, northern Burkina Faso. In June 2022 Mali’s military regime withdrew from the G5 Sahel.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">Somalia</heading>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In January 2007 the Peace and Security Council authorized the deployment of an AU Mission in Somalia (AMISOM), with a mandate to contribute to the political stabilization of Somalia. AMISOM became operational in May, having been endorsed by the UN Security Council.</p>
                    <p id="IO-AFUNION.890" usage="edio ass">
          A high-level Somalia Security Conference convened in December 2017, in the Somali capital, Mogadishu, addressed the need for representatives of the Somali authorities, the AU, AMISOM, the UN, the EU and other international partners to accelerate the co-ordinated development of a plan to guide a phased transition from AMISOM to a full Somali-led national security architecture. In May 2018 the UN Security Council tasked AMISOM with, 
          <i>inter alia,</i>
           continuing to reduce the threat from al-Shabaab (`the Youth’) militants and other armed opposition groups, engaging with communities and securing principal supply routes in areas previously under al-Shabaab control, securing key population centres, and mentoring the Somali military and police.
        </p>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In March 2021 the Chairperson of the AU Commission urged stakeholders in Somalia to engage in constructive dialogue, within the framework of an accord on an electoral model concluded on 17 September 2020 that aimed to resolve an ongoing impasse over the organization of elections (which were to have been held in February 2021, but had been postponed). In mid-April the AU and international partners collectively stated deep concern over a recent decision by the Somali legislature to replace the 17 September agreement with a different electoral process that entailed a lengthy extension to the current presidential and parliamentary mandates. Later in the month they strongly condemned an eruption of violence in Mogadishu, reiterating that adherence to the 17 September arrangement should represent the only model for the electoral process, and that an extension of government mandates would cause a destabilizing political crisis. They stated particular concern over emerging fragmentation of the Somali National Army into clan-based factions. The former President of Ghana, John Mahama, was appointed in May as the AU High Representative for Somalia to support the political negotiations; on 21 May, however, Mahama resigned, after the Somali authorities opposed his deployment and expressed doubt regarding his impartiality. In mid-2021 representatives of AMISOM, the UN, IGAD and the EU visited Somalia’s federal member states with the aim of fostering constructive engagement in the electoral preparations. In September AMISOM and the Somali military initiated a Joint Operations Coordination Centre in Mogadishu. In that month the AU Commission and AMISOM began to provide technical and advisory electoral assistance to the Somali authorities to support legislative elections that were initiated in November.</p>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In early March 2022 the AU Peace and Security Council determined to reconfigure AMISOM as the AU Transition Mission in Somalia (ATMIS); this transformation was endorsed on 31 March by the UN Security Council. ATMIS was tasked with reducing the threat posed by al-Shabaab, assisting efforts to build the capacity of the Somali security and police forces, supporting national peacebuilding and reconciliation activities, and with undertaking a phased transfer of security responsibilities to Somalia. In early May the Chairperson of the AU Commission strongly condemned an al-Shabaab terrorist attack that killed at least 10 Burundian ATMIS troops. In mid-May he congratulated the newly elected President of Somalia, Hassan Sheikh Mohamud (a presidential poll having completed a protracted Somalian electoral process). At the beginning of September a new Head of ATMIS and AU Special Representative to Somalia, Mohammed el-Amine Souef, took office. The ATMIS Forward Operating Base in Buulo Mareer, in the Lower Shabelle region, southwest of Mogadishu, was attacked by al-Shabaab suicide bombers in May 2023. A phased reduction of the mission’s personnel was initiated in that year, focused on a withdrawal deadline of December 2024: during 1 January-30 June 2024 the mission was to comprise up to 14,626 uniformed personnel.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">South Sudan</heading>
                    <p usage="ass edio">
          In accordance with a seven-point Roadmap for Action by Sudan and South Sudan, approved in April 2012 by the AU Peace and Security Council, and aimed at normalizing relations between the two states, both national militaries were withdrawn from the contested area of Abyei by the end of May. (See 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="IO-UNPKOS.UNISFA.1"> UN Interim Security Force for Abyei—UNISFA</xr>
           for further details.) In June 2015 Alpha Oumar Konaré—the former President of Mali and former Chairperson of the AU Commission—was appointed to the post of AU High Representative for South Sudan. An AU High-Level Ad Hoc Committee for South Sudan, chaired by South Africa and also comprising Algeria, Chad, Nigeria and Rwanda (the `C5’), was established by the Peace and Security Council to assist the peace process.
        </p>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">
           In January 2018 the AU Assembly commended the 
          <xr pageref="N" ref="IGAD.IO">Intergovernmental Authority on Development</xr>
           for its leadership of the inaugural session of a High Level Revitalization Forum, which had been convened in December 2017 to advance the implementation of the (August 2015) Agreement for the Resolution of the Conflict in South Sudan, and welcomed the signing by stakeholders in South Sudan, during the Forum, of an Agreement of Cessation of Hostilities, Protection of Civilians and Humanitarian Access. In September 2018 the Chairperson of the AU Commission welcomed the signature by the parties to the conflict of a new Revitalized Agreement on the Resolution of the Conflict in South Sudan. On 22 February 2020 President Salva Kiir and former Vice-President Riek Machar concluded a power-sharing agreement, formally ending the civil war. In accordance with the accord, a new Revitalized Transitional Government of National Unity (RTGoNU) was established. In that month the AU Assembly urged the international community to extend further logistical, financial and material assistance to the South Sudan Peace Process, and commended the AU C5’s ongoing efforts to support South Sudan. The AU High-Level Implementation Panel on Sudan (AUHIP, established in 2009) has continued to work towards facilitating agreement between South Sudan and Sudan over the future of Abyei. At the beginning of June 2021 a joint delegation that included representatives of the AU, UN Mission in South Sudan, and IGAD visited Pibor, in eastern South Sudan, where intercommunal violence had recently escalated. In August 2022 the Chairperson of the AU Commission welcomed the adoption by the RTGoNU of an Agreement on the Roadmap to a Peaceful and Democratic End to the Transitional Period in South Sudan; this extended by 24 months the transitional period provided for under the R-ARCSS, to 22 February 2025. The AU, IGAD and UN Mission in South Sudan formed a technical trilateral mechanism in August 2022 that was focused on supporting the process of drafting a permanent national constitution. On 23 February 2023 the RTGoNU asked the AU, UN and IGAD for assistance in establishing a joint taskforce to support the advancement of the constitution-making and electoral processes; the inaugural meeting of the new taskforce was convened on 1 June. In May the AU and IGAD jointly initiated a post-conflict needs assessment for South Sudan.
        </p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">Sudan</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">In July 2007 the UN Security Council authorized the establishment of a joint AU/UN Hybrid Operation in Darfur (UNAMID), in order to support the implementation and verification of the Darfur Peace Agreement, concluded between parties to the conflict in western Sudan in May 2006. The operation was also mandated to protect civilians, to provide security for humanitarian assistance, to support an inclusive political process, to contribute to the promotion of human rights and rule of law, and to monitor and report on the situation along the borders with Chad and the Central African Republic (CAR). UNAMID assumed command of the existing AU Mission in Sudan in December 2007. A joint AU-UN Chief Mediator was appointed in June 2008. A Joint Support Co-ordination Mechanism Office in Addis Ababa, comprising liaison officers and communications equipment, was established in November to ensure effective consultation between AU headquarters and the UN. In March 2009 an AU High-Level Panel on Darfur was established to address means of securing peace, justice and reconciliation in the territory. The panel issued a report of its findings and recommendations in October; a key recommendation was the creation of a hybrid court, comprising both AU and Sudanese judges, to prosecute crimes against humanity committed in Darfur. In March 2016 the Sudanese Government signed a Roadmap Agreement for Ending the Conflicts in Sudan, which had been negotiated under the auspices of the AUHIP on Sudan; the Roadmap was adopted by Sudanese opposition groups in early August. In late 2018 UNAMID transferred to the Sudanese Government 10 team sites in eastern and southern Darfur, in accordance with a UN Security Council resolution of July to reconfigure the operation. In January 2019 UNAMID relocated its headquarters from El Fasher to Zalingei, in central Darfur.</p>
                    <p usage="edio ass">In April 2019 the AU Peace and Security Council condemned as unconstitutional the overthrow of President Omar Hassan Ahmad al-Bashir by the Sudanese military and establishment of a military-led transitional government. The Council demanded the introduction of a civilian transitional political authority (to precede national elections) within 15 days, later extended to 60 days, with the threat of suspension from the organization if this was not achieved. At the beginning of June, in response to an escalation of civil unrest the Chairperson of the AU Commission called on Sudan’s Transitional Military Council to protect civilians, and reiterated demands that all Sudanese stakeholders should participate in negotiations aimed at achieving an inclusive accord providing for the establishment of the proposed civilian transitional authority. On 6 June—by which time paramilitary forces had reportedly killed more than 100 civilians and negotiations between opposition representatives and the interim military council had stalled—the AU suspended Sudan from participation in its activities, pending the introduction of civilian transitional rule. A political agreement, negotiated under AU auspices, was concluded in July, and a formal power-sharing arrangement was signed in early August. In early September, following the appointment of a new Prime Minister and cabinet, the AU Peace and Security Council resolved to lift Sudan’s suspension from the organization.</p>
                    <p usage="edio ass">In early September 2020 the Chairperson of the AU Commission welcomed the recent adoption by the SPLM-North faction (active in Darfur) of a statement of principles that backed a peace agreement that had been initialled on 31 August, in Juba, South Sudan, by the Transitional Government of Sudan and five opposition groupings (excluding SPLM-North). UNAMID officially ended its mandated operational phase on 31 December 2020, and entered a final six-month drawdown period on 1 January 2021. Meanwhile, a new UN political mission, the UN Integrated Transition Assistance Mission in Sudan, was established. Almost immediately, from January 2021, intercommunal violence escalated in El Geneina (West Darfur), as well as in Tawila (North Darfur) and East Jebel Marra (South Darfur), generating renewed population displacement in the region.</p>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">In mid-September 2021 the Chairperson of the AU Commission condemned an attempt by the military to seize power in Sudan. On 25 October the Transitional Government of Sudan was overthrown in a military coup, the transitional institutions dissolved and the civilian leadership detained. The Chairperson of the AU Commission stated `deep dismay’ at this development, and urged dialogue and the release of all the detained leaders. Although the Prime Minister, Abdalla Hamdok, was released on 26 October, he remained under the `close surveillance’ of the military, and other senior members of the transitional administration continued to be detained. Later that day the Peace and Security Council suspended Sudan from participation in the organization’s activities. Hamdok resigned the premiership in January 2022. In February the 35th AU ordinary Assembly stated deep concern over violent clashes that had intensified since 2021 at the Sudan-Ethiopia border. At the end of March 2022 the international Friends of Sudan Group (including Canada, France, Germany, Italy, the Netherlands, Norway, Saudi Arabia, Sweden, the United Arab Emirates and the UK) welcomed ongoing collaboration between the AU, IGAD and the then UN mission in Sudan (UNITAMS) to facilitate a political process aimed at resolving the political crisis in Sudan. From April the AU, IGAD and UNITAMS initiated a new phase of the process, convening discussions with stakeholders to the Juba Peace Agreement in order to advance more formal political dialogue. They issued a joint statement, as the Trilateral Mechanism, in mid-May urging a lifting of the country’s state of emergency and an end to violence on the part of the authorities, and reiterated their commitment to supporting the restoration of constitutional order. At the end of May Sudan’s military regime issued a decree ending the state of emergency. The Trilateral Mechanism aimed to initiate direct talks between the Sudanese stakeholders. The Trilateral Mechanism endorsed a new Political Framework Agreement signed in December by the military authorities and a coalition of civilian leaders, and initiated a series of workshops in the following month to strengthen the ongoing discussions regarding political transition; conclusive agreement remained elusive, however, including with regard to the proposed integration of the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) into the Sudanese Armed Forces (SAF). In mid-March 2023 the Trilateral Mechanism convened a National Conference: Towards Building a Sudanese Model for Justice and Transitional Justice, which issued a declaration of principles.</p>
                    <p>On 15 April 2023 the ongoing RSF-SAF tensions erupted into violent clashes across Khartoum and elsewhere, resulting in numerous fatalities. (The RSF—which was reportedly supported by the Russian Wagner Group—soon claimed to have taken control of Khartoum International Airport, provincial airports and the presidential palace.) The President of the AU Commission called for an immediate end to the hostilities. On 20 April a meeting to discuss means of addressing the crisis, convened (in a virtual format) between the AU Commission Chairperson, UN Secretary-General, Arab League Secretary-General, and Executive Secretary of IGAD, established an Expanded Mechanism on the Sudan Crisis. The Expanded Mechanism—comprising representatives of the Trilateral Mechanism, Arab League, EU, the five permanent members of the UN Security Council (the `P5’), the three African member states then serving on the Council, states neighbouring Sudan, states designated at that time by IGAD to mediate in the dispute (Djibouti, Kenya and South Sudan; Ethiopia was subsequently added), the then AU Chair (Comoros), and other international stakeholders—was tasked with co-ordinating and harmonizing subregional, continental and international efforts to facilitate a peaceful resolution of the conflict. From 6 May RSF and SAF negotiating teams participated in talks mediated by Saudi Arabia and the USA, in Jeddah (Saudi Arabia). A Jeddah Declaration of Commitment to Protect the Civilians of Sudan was signed by the SAF and RSF on 11 May. Meanwhile, several short-lived ceasefire agreements were implemented. On 31 May the SAF suspended its participation in the Jeddah-based talks, having accused the RSF of lack of commitment. On 1 June punitive sanctions were imposed by the USA on interests associated with both the SAF and RSF; the UK imposed similar sanctions in mid-July. Meanwhile, in late May the AU’s Peace and Security Council, meeting at the level of heads of state and of government, adopted an AU Roadmap for the Resolution of the Conflict in Sudan, which had been formulated in close collaboration with Sudanese stakeholders; this advocated for the peace process to be led jointly by the AU, IGAD, Arab League, UN, and other partners. Sudan’s leadership noted in response that the country was suspended from the AU. In mid-July the SAF and RSF—as well as states neighbouring Sudan, the AU Commission Chairperson, and the Arab League Secretary-General—participated in a summit in the Egyptian capital, Cairo, that was chaired by that country’s President, Abd al-Fatah al-Sisi. In mid-July the International Criminal Court initiated an investigation into alleged war crimes committed during the conflict. The second meeting of an IGAD Quartet Group of Countries for the Resolution of the Situation in the Republic of Sudan, with participation by the Chairperson of the African Commission, was convened in early September 2023—by which time several thousand people had been killed, injured or displaced as a result of the crisis in Sudan. (The first meeting had been held in July.) The Quartet noted with concern that the conflict was escalating, and that its scope was extending into outlying regions; and suggested that all ongoing relevant peace initiatives should be consolidated, within the framework of an all-inclusive platform to be led jointly by IGAD and the AU. The Quartet requested IGAD and the AU to advance preparations for a political dialogue on a Sudanese-owned political process. IGAD’s diplomatic efforts, however, subsequently faltered (q.v.). In December the Expanded Mechanism, convened by the AU Commission, demanded that the SAF and RSF agree to a ceasefire, with a view to resuming a peaceful return to a transition to civilian constitutional rule in Sudan. The Mechanism also called on both parties to facilitate safe humanitarian access to civilians. Support was reaffirmed for the AU Roadmap for the Resolution of the Conflict in Sudan, as well as for a parallel IGAD roadmap on Sudan. A new AU High-Level Panel for Sudan was appointed in early 2024. In February a meeting of the Expanded Mechanism was organized to liaise with the Panel. In early March the Chairperson of the AU Commission urged the warring parties in Sudan (without success) to observe a ceasefire during Ramadan.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio">Zimbabwe</heading>
                    <p usage="edio">An AU-COMESA Election Observation Mission that was dispatched to observe a general election held in August 2023 in Zimbabwe subsequently issued a preliminary report which stated that, in spite of logistical challenges, the elections had been conducted in a generally peaceful and transparent manner.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio">Other Sanctions</heading>
                    <p usage="edio">
          In August 2008, following the overthrow of its constitutional Government in a military 
          <i>coup d'état</i>
          , Mauritania was suspended from participating in the activities of the AU. Guinea was suspended from the AU during December 2008-December 2010, also following a 
          <i>coup d'état</i>
          ; Guinea's membership suspension was lifted in view of presidential elections held in 2010. In February 2010 Niger was suspended from participation in AU activities, following a 
          <i>coup d'état</i>
          ; Niger's membership suspension was lifted in March 2011, following the successful organization, in October 2010, of a referendum on a new constitution, and of legislative and presidential elections in early 2011. In March 2009 the AU suspended Madagascar from participation in its activities, following the forced resignation of the elected President, Mark Ravalomanana, and transfer of power to the military; following the election, in late 2013, of Hery Rajaonarimampianina as its new President, Madagascar was readmitted to the Union in January 2014. In April 2012, in view of the overthrow by a military coup of the legitimate government of Guinea-Bissau, that country was suspended from participation in AU meetings; in view of legislative elections, held in April 2014, and a presidential election held in two rounds in April and May of that year, Guinea-Bissau was readmitted in mid-June to full participation in the activities of the Union.
        </p>
               </p-group>
               <!--Committee of Intelligence and Security Service in Africa - CISSA -->
          </int-org-section>
          <int-org-section id="AU.IO.INTCOOP.1" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
               <heading>International Co-operation</heading>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass ewyb">EU-Africa Summits</heading>
                    <p usage="edio">In April 2000 the first EU-Africa summit of heads of state and of government was held in Cairo. The second EU-Africa summit meeting was initially to have been held in April 2003 but was postponed, owing to disagreements concerning the participation of President Mugabe of Zimbabwe, against whom the EU had imposed sanctions. Held eventually in December 2007, in Lisbon, Portugal, the summit adopted a Joint&#160;Africa-EU Strategy (JAES), outlining a long-term vision of the future partnership between the two regions. Convened in Brussels, Belgium, in April 2014, the fourth EU-Africa summit adopted a Pan-African Programme, which aimed to support the AU’s continental integration vision during 2014-20, at a total cost of €845m. The objectives of the programme included improving trade relations and increasing mobility across regions, and strengthening the continental response to transnational challenges, including security, migration and climate change. A Joint Africa-EU Task Force meets regularly to consider areas of co-operation. The fifth EU-Africa summit was convened in November 2017, in Abidjan, Côte d’Ivoire, with a focus on `Youth’. A joint AU-EU-UN Task Force on Migration was established to address the ongoing migrant crisis in Libya.</p>
                    <p usage="ewyb ass">The inaugural EU-Africa summit of heads of state and of government was held in 2000, in Cairo. The second summit, held in December 2007, in Lisbon, Portugal, adopted a Joint&#160;Africa-EU Strategy (JAES), outlining a long-term vision of the future partnership between the two regions. A Joint Africa-EU Task Force meets regularly to consider areas of co-operation.</p>
                    <p usage="ewyb edio ass">The sixth EU-Africa summit was convened in February 2022, in Brussels, Belgium. An €150,000m. Africa-Europe Investment Package was announced, and the EU reaffirmed a commitment to donate 450m. COVID-19 vaccine doses to Africa. An EU-Africa Business Forum was held alongside the summit, in a hybrid (online and in-person) format.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading>Forum on China-Africa Cooperation</heading>
                    <p>
          Co-operation between African states and China is undertaken within the framework of the Forum on China-Africa Cooperation (FOCAC). The first FOCAC ministerial conference was held in October 2000, and subsequently conferences have been held every three years. The eighth FOCAC ministerial meeting, held in late November 2021, in Dakar, Senegal, adopted a China-Africa Cooperation Vision 2035; the Dakar Action Plan covering 2022-24 (the first phase of Vision 2035); the Sino-African Declaration on Climate Change; and a general Declaration. Nine programmes were to be implemented under the Dakar Action Plan. These included a medical and health programme, under which, 
          <i>inter alia,</i>
           China was to donate 600m. further COVID-19 vaccine doses to Africa, and to provide 400m. doses through joint Chinese-African production; poverty reduction, agricultural, and trade and investment programmes; a digital innovation programme; green initiatives; capacity building support; cultural initiatives; and a peace and security programme (which was to include military assistance to the AU). Addressing the conference by videolink, China’s President Xi Jinping pledged continued support for expanding Africa’s local capacity for COVID-19 vaccine production. A reduced Chinese financial commitment, totalling US&#8201;$40,000m., was made for 2022-24, compared with $60,000m. in 2019-21. (Concerns over some African nations’ debt dependency on China had been raised in recent years.) Themed `Deepen China-Africa Partnership and Promote Sustainable Development to Build a China-Africa Community with a Shared Future in the New Era’, the eighth FOCAC focused on Africa-China co-operation in aligning synergies between the Belt and Road Initiative (launched by China in 2013, with the aim of developing infrastructure and trade along traditional routes between Asia, Europe and Africa), the AU’s Agenda 2063, the UN’s 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, and the national development strategies of African states. The seventh China-Africa Business Forum was staged alongside the conference. From 2014 China superseded the USA as Africa’s primary source of foreign direct investment.
        </p>
                    <p usage="edio ass">A Ministerial Forum of China-Africa Health Development was held in October 2016, in Cape Town, South Africa. In August 2018 the interim secretariat of a new China-Africa Environmental Cooperation Centre (approved by the sixth FOCAC, held in December 2015) was inaugurated in Nairobi. An AU office opened in Beijing in October.</p>
                    <p usage="edio ass">An extraordinary China-Africa Summit on Solidarity against COVID-19—jointly proposed by China, the AU and the FOCAC chairmanship—was convened by videoconference in mid-June 2020. The third session of an AU-China Human Rights Dialogue was held (in a virtual format) in September 2021.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass">Africa-Caribbean Community</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">An inaugural Africa-Caribbean Community summit meeting was convened, in a virtual format, in September 2021.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading>Africa-UN Co-operation</heading>
                    <p>In April 2017 the AU Chairperson and UN Secretary-General signed a framework agreement aimed at consolidating co-operation between their respective organizations in the area of peace and security. In this context, in September the AU Commissioner for Peace and Security and the UN Assistant Secretary-General for Peacebuilding Support concluded an MOU on a UN-AU Partnership in Peacebuilding. An AU-UN Joint Declaration on Co-operation for AU Peace Support Operations was signed by the AU Commission Chair and the UN Secretary-General in December 2018; this outlined principles to guide future joint responses to conflicts and political crises in Africa. An inaugural AU-UN Periodic Coordination Meeting was convened (in a virtual format) in June 2022 between AU Commissioners and senior representatives of the UN, including from the ECA and UNDP, which aimed to enhance efforts to achieve internationally agreed development goals. The Seventh AU-UN Annual Conference was convened in New York, USA, in November 2023.</p>
               </p-group>
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="edio ass">AU-Russia Co-operation</heading>
                    <p usage="edio ass">The second AU-Russia summit and Russia-Africa Economic and Humanitarian Forum were organized in July 2023, in St Petersburg, Russian Federation (the inaugural AU-Russia summit having been held in October 2019). Russia reportedly offered to provide up to 50,000 metric tons of free grain to six African countries (Burkina Faso, CAR, Eritrea, Mali, Somalia and Zimbabwe).</p>
               </p-group>
               <!--~ http://hrst.au.int/en/content/au-commission-holds-experts%E2%80%99-workshop-designing-african-space-strategy 4th ASA summit Ecuador -->
               <p-group>
                    <heading usage="ewyb edio ass">United States-Africa Leaders Summit</heading>
                    <p>A second United States-Africa Leaders Summit was convened in December 2022, in Washington, DC, USA (the first having been held in 2014). Initiatives approved at that time included an Advisory Council on African Diaspora Engagement in the USA and a United States-Africa Space Forum. US President Biden confirmed his support for the AU’s accession to permanent membership of the G20 (achieved in September 2023), and the USA pledged funding of US&#8201;$55,000m. to advance collective priorities, in the framework of the AU Agenda 2063.</p>
               </p-group>
          </int-org-section>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.110" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Finance</heading>
          <p>In mid-2022 the AU Executive Council agreed a budget of US&#8201;$654.8m. for 2023. Some 33% of expenditure (including the whole operating budget) was to be derived from assessed contributions from member states, and the remaining 67% from partners. The AU Foundation, inaugurated in February 2014, aims to mobilize voluntary contributions towards the financing of development priorities throughout the continent.</p>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="AU.IO.45" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Publications</heading>
          <publ-list>
               <publ-entry>
                    <publ-name>Africa’s Development Dynamics</publ-name>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">annually, AU/OECD Development Centre</content-note>
               </publ-entry>
               <publ-entry>
                    <publ-name>African Human Rights Yearbook</publ-name>
               </publ-entry>
               <publ-entry>
                    <publ-name>AU Echo</publ-name>
               </publ-entry>
               <publ-entry>
                    <publ-name>AU Handbook</publ-name>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">annually</content-note>
               </publ-entry>
          </publ-list>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.116" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF">
          <heading>Specialized Agencies</heading>
          <org-list>
               <org-entry id="IO.AU.10" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>Africa Centres for Disease Control and Prevention</org-entry-name>
                         <alt-name>Africa CDC</alt-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>POB 3243, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">(11) 5517700</telephone>
                         <email>africacdc@africa-union.org</email>
                         <internet>africacdc.org</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>2017</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">aims to support AU member states in responding to public health emergencies</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">comprises Regional Collaborating Centres in Libreville, Gabon (for Central Africa), Nairobi, Kenya (East Africa), Cairo, Egypt (North Africa), Lusaka, Zambia (Southern Africa), and Abuja, Nigeria (West Africa)</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">supports region-wide surveillance, public health information activities, and works to strengthen public health institutes and networks of laboratories</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">in March 2020 adopted an Africa Joint Continental Strategy for the COVID-19 Outbreak; from Sept. worked with WHO to establish a COVID-19 sequencing network of laboratories</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">during 2021 a digital CDC COVID-19 Travel Pass was developed</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">in April 2021 launched, with the AU, a Partnerships for African Vaccine Manufacturing (PAVM) framework</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">organized in Dec. the inaugural International Conference on Public Health in Africa</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">in July 2022 the AU Exec. Council approved a revised statute of Africa CDC to enable it to become an autonomous public health agency</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">in Oct. 2023 launched a Multisectoral Task Force on Non-Communicable Diseases, Injuries and Mental Health</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">was to co-host in June 2024, with the French Govt, an event at which a new African Vaccine Manufacturing Accelerator was to be launched</content-note>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Dir</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <title>Dr</title>
                                   <forename>Jean</forename>
                                   <surname>Kaseya</surname>
                              </person-name>
                              <person-note>DRC</person-note>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <org-entry media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF" usage="ewyb edio ass">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>African Academy of Languages (ACALAN)</org-entry-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>ACI 2000 Hamdallaye, Porte 223, rue 394 Bamako, Mali</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">20-29-04-59</telephone>
                         <fax>20-29-04-57</fax>
                         <email>info@acalan.tv</email>
                         <internet>acalan-au.org</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>2006</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">fosters continental integration and devt through the promotion of the use—in all domains—of African languages</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">aims to restore the role and vitality of indigenous languages (estimated to number around 2,035), and to reverse the negative impact of colonialism on their perceived value</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">works through a framework of National Language Structures and Vehicular Cross-border Language Commissions</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">implements a Training of African Languages Teachers and Media Practitioners Project</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">promotes a Pan-African Masters and PhD Program in African Languages and Applied Linguistics (PANMAPAL), inaugurated in 2006 at the University of Yaoundé 1 (Cameroon), Addis Ababa University (Ethiopia), and at the University of Cape Town (South Africa)</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">in Feb. 2022 the 35th AU Assembly endorsed Kiswahili as an org.-wide working language</content-note>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Exec. Sec.</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <title>Prof.</title>
                                   <forename>Lang Fafa</forename>
                                   <surname>Dampha</surname>
                              </person-name>
                              <person-note>The Gambia</person-note>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <org-entry id="WB0231XB.IO.TXT.50" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF" usage="ewyb edio ass mena">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>African Capacity Building Foundation (ACBF)</org-entry-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>2 Fairbairn Dr., Mount Pleasant, Harare, Zimbabwe</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">(4) 304663</telephone>
                         <email>root@acbf-pact.org</email>
                         <internet>www.acbf-pact.org</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>1991 by the World Bank, UNDP, the AfDB, African govts and bilateral donors; designated a specialized agency of the AU in 2017</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">aims to build sustainable human and institutional capacity for sustainable growth, poverty reduction and good governance in Africa</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">identifies strategies to support the implementation of the AU’s Agenda 2063 strategic framework for the long-term socioeconomic transformation of Africa</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">hosts the secretariat of an African Think Tank Network, and, since 2014, has organized an annual Africa Think Tank Summit to promote the exchange of innovative solutions and peer learning aimed at advancing Africa’s devt agenda </content-note>
                    <stats>mems: 36 African and 13 non-African govts, the AfDB, World Bank and UNDP</stats>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Exec. Sec.</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <title>Prof.</title>
                                   <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                                   <surname>Nnadozie</surname>
                              </person-name>
                              <person-note>Nigeria</person-note>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <!--Think Tank Platform Project for Africa-->
               <org-entry id="WB02062.IO.TXT.93" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                    <data-protection date-added="21.06.2016" ticked-box="Y" />
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>African Civil Aviation Commission (AFCAC)</org-entry-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>1 route de l’Aéroport International LSS, BP 8898, Dakar, Senegal</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">33-859-88-00</telephone>
                         <fax>33-820-70-18</fax>
                         <email>secretariat@afcac.org</email>
                         <internet>afcac.org</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>1969 jtly by the OAU and International Civil Aviation Organization</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">became an AU specialized agency in 1978</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">promotes co-ordination and better utilization and devt of African air transport systems and the standardization of aircraft, flight equipment and training progs for pilots and mechanics</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">organizes working groups and seminars, and compiles statistics</content-note>
                    <stats>mems: 54 states</stats>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Sec.-Gen.</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <forename>Adefunke</forename>
                                   <surname>Adeyemi</surname>
                              </person-name>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <!--~ African Medicines Agency-->
               <org-entry media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>African Risk Capacity (ARC)</org-entry-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>Bldg 1, Sunhill Park, 1 Eglin Rd, Sunninghill, 2157 Johannesburg, South Africa</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">(11) 5171535</telephone>
                         <email>info@arc.int</email>
                         <internet>www.africanriskcapacity.org</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>2012 under the African Risk Capacity Establishment Agreement (which had 36 signatories and had been ratified by 11 states at Jan. 2024)</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">aims to finance risk resistance and contingency measures</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">uses satellite weather surveillance and World Food Programme-developed software to assess, and disburse immediate funding to, mem. states affected by a natural disaster</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">in May 2016 the ARC signed MOUs with the AfDB and the Conférence Inter-Africaine des Marchés d’Assurance on future collaboration in planning, preparation and response to extreme weather events and natural disasters</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">they concluded a further MOU in Aug. 2017 affirming co-operation on strengthening mechanisms to manage weather-related risk</content-note>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Dir-Gen.</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <forename>Ibrahima</forename>
                                   <surname>Cheikh Diong</surname>
                              </person-name>
                              <person-note>Senegal</person-note>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <org-entry id="WB02062.10.TXT.2908051128" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>African Telecommunications Union (ATU)</org-entry-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>ATU Secretariat, POB 35282 Nairobi, 00200 Kenya</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">(20) 2322120</telephone>
                         <fax>(20) 2322124</fax>
                         <email>sg@atuuat.africa</email>
                         <internet>atuuat.africa</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>1999 as successor to Pan-African Telecommunications Union (f. 1977)</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">promotes the devt of information communications in Africa, with the aim of making Africa an equal participant in the global information society</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">works towards universal service and access and full inter-country connectivity</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">promotes devt and adoption of appropriate policies and regulatory frameworks and the financing of devt</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">encourages co-operation between mems and the exchange of information</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">advocates the harmonization of telecommunications policies</content-note>
                    <stats>mems: 51; 61 assoc. mems comprising fixed and mobile telecoms operators</stats>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Sec.-Gen.</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <forename>John</forename>
                                   <surname>Omo</surname>
                              </person-name>
                              <person-note>Kenya</person-note>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <org-entry id="OTHER.IO.ASS.67" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF" usage="edio ass">
                    <!--~ moved to AU-IBAR to AU from small orgs 27.ix.2023-->
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>African Union-Interafrican Bureau for Animal Resources</org-entry-name>
                         <abbr>AU-IBAR</abbr>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>Kenindia Business Park, Museum Hill, Westlands Rd, POB 30786, Nairobi, Kenya</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">(20) 3674000</telephone>
                         <fax>(20) 3674341</fax>
                         <email>ibar.office@au-ibar.org</email>
                         <internet>www.au-ibar.org</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>1951 as the Interafrican Bureau of Epizootic Diseases, subsequently renamed</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">a specialized technical office of the AU Commission</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">works at the continental level and with African RECs to develop Africa’s animal resources, incl. fisheries, livestock and wildlife</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">in 2012 declared the eradication across the continent of Rinderpest (a viral disease affecting ruminants)</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">acts as secretariat of the International Scientific Council for Trypanosomiasis Research and Control (ISCTRC)</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">projects ongoing in 2024 incl. FishGov2, Africa Blue Economy Strategy, Resilient Africa Feed and Fodder Systems, and One Health Data Alliance Africa</content-note>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Dir</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <title>Dr</title>
                                   <forename>Huyam Ahmed Mohammed</forename>
                                   <surname>Elamin Salih</surname>
                              </person-name>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <org-entry id="AU-IO.GGW.22" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>Pan-African Agency of the Great Green Wall</org-entry-name>
                         <alt-name>Agence Panafricaine de la Grande Muraille Vert</alt-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>Lot 414, ilot C, Nouakchott RIM, Mauritania</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">45-25-56-88</telephone>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>2010</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">co-ordinates implementation of the Great Green Wall initiative</content-note>
                    <stats>mems: 11 govts</stats>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Chair.</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <forename>Mohamed H.</forename>
                                   <surname>Abdullahi</surname>
                              </person-name>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <!--~ Pan-African E-Network Project Africa-->
               <org-entry id="WB02062.IO.TXT.95" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF" usage="edio ass">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>Pan-African News Agency (PANAPRESS)</org-entry-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>BP 4056, Dakar, Senegal</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">33-869-12-34</telephone>
                         <fax>33-824-13-90</fax>
                         <email>marketing@panapress.com</email>
                         <internet>www.panapress.com</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>1979 as Pan­African News Agency, restructured under current name in 1997</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">regional offices in Khartoum, Sudan</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">Lusaka, Zambia</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">Kinshasa, DRC</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">Lagos, Nigeria</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">Tripoli, Libya</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">began operations in May 1983</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">receives information from national news agencies and circulates news in Arabic, English, French and Portuguese</content-note>
               </org-entry>
               <org-entry id="WB02062.IO.TXT.96" media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF" usage="edio ass">
                    <!--rc 26.02.2021 website not working-->
                    <data-protection date-added="13.07.2017" ticked-box="Y" />
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>Pan-African Postal Union (PAPU)</org-entry-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>Plot III, Block Z Golf Course, Sekei, POB 6026, Arusha, Tanzania</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">(27) 2543263</telephone>
                         <email>sc@papu.co.tz</email>
                         <internet>www.upap-papu.africa</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>1980</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">facilitates co-operation among mem. states in the improvement of postal services</content-note>
                    <stats>mems: 45 countries</stats>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Sec.-Gen.</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <forename>Sifundo Chief</forename>
                                   <surname>Moyo</surname>
                              </person-name>
                              <person-note>Zimbabwe</person-note>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">
          publ. 
          <publ-name>PAPU News</publ-name>
                    </content-note>
               </org-entry>
               <org-entry media="PRINTANDONLINE" print-only="NO" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="ORG-ENTRYREF">
                    <org-entry-head>
                         <org-entry-name>
            Pan African University 
            <abbr>PAU</abbr>
                         </org-entry-name>
                         <alt-name>Université Panafricaine</alt-name>
                    </org-entry-head>
                    <address-block>
                         <address type="POSTAL">
                              <verbatim-address>(Rectorate) BP 5383, Yaoundé, Cameroon</verbatim-address>
                         </address>
                         <telephone alsofax="N">(222) 217090</telephone>
                         <internet>pau-au.africa</internet>
                    </address-block>
                    <found-date>2011; Governing Council inaugurated in 2015</found-date>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">aims to develop a network of academic and research centres of excellence across Africa offering postgraduate training in the areas of science, technology, innovation, social sciences and governance</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">comprises the following specialized institutes: the PAU Institute for Basic Sciences, Technology and Innovation (PAUSTI) (based in Juja, Kenya); PAU Institute for Life and Earth Sciences—including Health and Agriculture (PAULESI) (in Ibadan, Nigeria); PAU Institute for Governance, Humanities and Social Sciences (PAUGHSS) (Yaoundé, Cameroon); the PAU Institute for Water and Energy Sciences—including Climate Change (PAUWES) (Tlemcen, Algeria); and the PAU Virtual and E-University (launched in Nov. 2019) which offers online learning progs</content-note>
                    <content-note style="NORMAL">the establishment of a South Africa-based PAU Institute for Space Sciences (PAUSS) was pending</content-note>
                    <role-group>
                         <role>Rector</role>
                         <person>
                              <person-name>
                                   <title>Prof.</title>
                                   <forename>Jean</forename>
                                   <surname>Koulidiati</surname>
                              </person-name>
                         </person>
                    </role-group>
               </org-entry>
               <!--~ Supreme Council for Sport in Africa (SCSA), f. 1996, dissolved end-July 2013; 5th Conference of African Union Ministers of Sports meeting - 25-26 July 2013, Abidjan; implementation of the African Sport Architecture Put in ACBF for EDIO, ASS, MENA-->
          </org-list>
          <p usage="ewyb">A Pan-African Postal Union is located in Arusha, Tanzania.</p>
     </int-org-section>
     <int-org-section id="WB02062.IO.TXT.118" sllink="SLSDOC" slsdocrf="INT-ORG-SECTREF" usage="edio">
          <heading>Summary of Constitutive Act of the African Union</heading>
          <heading-note>adopted at Lomé, Togo, on 11 July 2000; entered into force on 26 May 2001</heading-note>
          <legal-block>
               <gen-list>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.119">
                              <i>Article I</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.120">Definition of terms and abbreviations used in the Constitutive Act.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.121">
                              <i>Article 2</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.122">Establishment of the African Union in accordance with the provisions of the Act.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p>
                              <i>Article 3</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.123">The objectives of the Union shall be:</p>
                    </item>
               </gen-list>
               <gen-list>
                    <label>(a)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To achieve greater unity and solidarity between the African countries and their peoples.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(b)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To defend the sovereignty, territorial integrity and independence of its Member States.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(c)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To accelerate the political and socioeconomic integration of the continent.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(d)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To promote and defend African common positions on issues of interest to the continent and its peoples.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(e)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To encourage international co-operation, taking due account of the Charter of the United Nations and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(f)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To promote peace, security, and stability on the continent.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(g)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To promote democratic principles and institutions, popular participation and good governance.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(h)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To promote and protect human and peoples' rights in accordance with the African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights and other relevant human rights instruments.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(i)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To establish the necessary conditions which enable the continent to play its rightful role in the global economy and in international negotiations.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(j)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To promote sustainable development at the economic, social and cultural levels as well as the integration of African economies.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(k)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To promote co-operation in all fields of human activity to raise the living standards of African peoples.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(l)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To co-ordinate and harmonize policies between existing and future Regional Economic Communities for the gradual attainment of the objectives of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(m)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To advance the development of the continent by promoting research in all fields, in particular in science and technology.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(n)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>To work with relevant international partners in the eradication of preventable diseases and the promotion of good health on the continent.</p>
                    </item>
               </gen-list>
               <gen-list>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.124">
                              <i>Article 4</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
               </gen-list>
               <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.125">The Union shall function in accordance with the following principles:</p>
               <gen-list>
                    <label>(a)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Sovereign equality and interdependence among Member States of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(b)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Respect of borders existing on achievement of independence.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(c)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Participation of the African peoples in the activities of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(d)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Establishment of a common defence policy for the African Continent.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(e)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Peaceful resolution of conflicts among Member States of the Union through such appropriate means as may be decided upon by the Assembly.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(f)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Prohibition of the use of force or threat to use force among Member States of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(g)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Non-interference by any Member State in the internal affairs of another.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(h)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>The right of the Union to intervene in a Member State pursuant to a decision of the Assembly in respect of grave circumstances, namely war crimes, genocide and crimes against humanity.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(i)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Peaceful co-existence of Member States and their right to live in peace and security.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(j)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>The right of Member States to request intervention from the Union in order to restore peace and security.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(k)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Promotion of self-reliance within the framework of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(l)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Promotion of gender equality.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(m)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Respect for democratic principles, human rights, the rule of law and good governance.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(n)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Promotion of social justice to ensure balanced economic development.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(o)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Respect for the sanctity of human life, condemnation and rejection of impunity and political assassination, acts of terrorism and subversive activities.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(p)</label>
                    <item>
                         <p>Condemnation and rejection of unconstitutional changes of governments.</p>
                    </item>
               </gen-list>
               <gen-list>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.126">
                              <i>Article 5</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.127">Establishment of the organs of the Union: the Assembly of the Union; the Executive Council; the Pan-African Parliament; the Court of Justice; the Commission; the Permanent Representatives Committee; the Specialized Technical Committees; the Economic, Social, and Cultural Council; and the Financial Institutions.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.128">
                              <i>Articles 6-9</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.129">The Assembly of Heads of State and Government is the supreme organ of the Union. The Assembly meets at least once a year in ordinary session and, at the request of any Member State and on approval by a two-thirds majority of the Member States, may meet in extraordinary session. The Assembly determines the common policies of the Union; takes decisions on reports and recommendations from the other organs of the Union; may establish other organs of the Union; monitors the implementation of policies and decisions of the Union and ensures compliance by all Member States; adopts the budget of the Union; gives directives to the Executive Council on the management of conflicts, war and other emergency situations and the restoration of peace; makes and terminates the appointment of judges of the Court of Human and Peoples’ Rights; appoints the Chairperson of the Commission and his or her deputy or deputies and the Commissioners of the Commission and determines their functions and terms of office. The Assembly may delegate any of its powers and functions to any organ of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.132">
                              <i>Articles 10-13</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.133">The Executive Council, composed of the ministers of foreign affairs or other ministers or authorities designated by the member states, and responsible to the Assembly, co-ordinates and takes decisions on policies in areas of common interest to the Member States, including: foreign trade; energy, industry and mineral resources; food, agricultural and animal resources, livestock production and forestry; water resources and irrigation; environmental protection, humanitarian action and disaster response and relief; transport and communications; insurance; education, culture, health and human resources development; science and technology; nationality, residency and immigration matters; social security; establishment of a system of African rewards, medals and prizes.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.136">
                              <i>Articles 14-16</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.137">Establishment of the Specialized Technical Committees on: Rural Economy and Agricultural Matters; Monetary and Financial Affairs; Trade, Customs, and Immigration Matters; Industry, Science and Technology, Energy, Natural Resources and Environment; Transport Communications and Tourism; Health Labour and Social Affairs; and Education Culture and Human. Each Committee prepares, co-ordinates and reviews projects and programmes of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.138">
                              <i>Article 17</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.139">Concerns the establishment of a Pan-African Parliament to ensure the full participation of African peoples in the development and economic integration of the continent. (The composition, powers, functions and organization of the Parliament shall be defined in a protocol relating thereto.)</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.140">
                              <i>Article 18</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.141">Establishment of a Court of Justice. (The composition, functions and organization of the Court shall be defined in a protocol relating thereto.)</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.142">
                              <i>Article 19</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.143">Establishment of the financial institutions of the Union (whose rules and regulations shall be defined in protocols relating thereto): the African Central Bank; the African Monetary Fund; and the African Investment Bank.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.144">
                              <i>Article 20</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.145">Establishment of a Commission of the Union to act as the Union’s Secretariat.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.146">
                              <i>Article 21</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.147">Establishment of a Permanent Representatives Committee responsible for preparing the work of the Executive Council and acting on the instructions of the Council.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.148">
                              <i>Article 22</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.149">Establishment of the Economic, Social and Cultural Council, composed of different social and professional groups from Union Member States, as an advisory organ.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.150">
                              <i>Article 23</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.151">The Assembly shall determine the appropriate sanctions to be imposed on any Member State that defaults on payment of its contributions to the budget of the Union in the following manner: denial of the right to speak at meetings, to vote, to present candidates for any position or post within the Union, or to benefit from any activity or commitments therefrom. Furthermore, any Member State that fails to comply with the decisions and policies of the Union may be subject to sanctions, such as the denial of transport and communications links with other Member States or other measures of a political or economic nature.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.152">
                              <i>Article 24</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.153">Establishment of the Headquarters of the Union in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.154">
                              <i>Article 25</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.155">The working languages of the Union and all its institutions shall be African languages, Arabic, English, French and Portuguese. (In February 2020 the AU Assembly decided that Spanish should also be used as an official working language.)</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.156">
                              <i>Article 26</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.157">The Court shall be seized with matters of interpretation arising from the application or implementation of the Act. (Pending its establishment such matters shall be submitted to the Assembly of the Union, which shall decide by a two-thirds majority.)</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.162">
                              <i>Article 29</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.163">Any African State may notify the Chairperson of the Commission of its intention to accede to this Act and to be admitted as a member of the Union. Admission shall be decided by a simple majority of the Member States.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.164">
                              <i>Article 30</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.165">Governments that come to power through unconstitutional means shall not be allowed to participate in the activities of the Union.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.166">
                              <i>Article 31</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.167">Any State wishing to withdraw from the Union must give one year’s written notification to the Chairperson of the Commission.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.168">
                              <i>Article 32</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.169">Amendments or revisions of this Act may be submitted to the Chairperson of the Commission by any Member State and shall be adopted by the Assembly by consensus or by a two-thirds majority.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.170">
                              <i>Article 33</i>
                         </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                         <p id="WB02062.IO.TXT.171">This Act replaces the Charter of the Organization of African Unity. It takes precedence over and supersedes any inconsistent or contrary provisions of the Treaty establishing the African Economic Community.</p>
                    </item>
               </gen-list>
          </legal-block>
     </int-org-section>
     <!--08.iv.24 21,413 words inc. Const. Act-->
</int-org-entry>